<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Mathblogging.org -- Comments</title>
    <link>http://mathblogging.org/</link>
    <updated>2015-09-17T19:38:36Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mathblogging.org</name>
        <email>info@mathblogging.org</email>
        <uri>https://mathblogging.org</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mathblogging.org/"/>
    <subtitle>Your one stop shop for mathematical blogs</subtitle>
    <logo>http://mathblogging.org/logo.png</logo>
    <rights>No copyright asserted over individual posts; see original posts for copyright and/or licensing.</rights>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The conjugacy problem for automorphism groups of countable homogeneous structures by The conjugacy problem for automorphism groups of homogeneous digraphs]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/conjugacy/#comment-8324</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/conjugacy/#comment-8324">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-15T20:27:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] as several other homogeneous structures, have already been addressed in previous articles (here and here). In this article we complete the program, and establish a dichotomy theorem that this complexity [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Every countable model of set theory embeds into its own constructible universe by Ali Sadegh Daghighi]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4584</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4584">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-15T08:23:04Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Regarding the question 32 in your paper:</p>
<p>Can there be an embedding $j : V \rightarrow L$ when $V \neq L$?</p>
<p>You continued as follows:</p>
<p>&#8230; More generally, if $j$ is merely a class in Godel-Bernays set theory, then the existence of an embedding $j : V \rightarrow L$ implies global choice, since from the class $j$ we can pull back the L-order. For these reasons, we cannot expect every model of $ZFC$ or of $GB$ to have such embeddings. Can they be added generically? &#8230;</p>
<p>My question is: </p>
<p>Did you examine the existence of such an embedding in a universe which $V=L[R]$? </p>
<p>I ask this in connection with Jensen&#8217;s coding theorem which allows us to always go to code the entire universe with a real in a generic extension made by a class forcing.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Every countable model of set theory embeds into its own constructible universe by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4547</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4547">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-14T21:55:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Large cardinals generally give you elementary embeddings, which are therefore also embeddings in this weaker model-theoretic strength, but the converse is not generally the case. For example, in the paper I point out that it is a ZFC theorem that there is a nontrivial embedding $j:V\to V$; and so since every model of ZFC has such embeddings, their existence can carry no large cardinal strength.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Every countable model of set theory embeds into its own constructible universe by Ali]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4541</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-model-embeds-into-own-constructible-universe/#comment-4541">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-14T16:37:16Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Does the lack of elementarity in this type of embeddings mean the lack of any relation between them and large cardinal axioms? </p>
<p>A review on the original construction of a non-trivial elementary embedding derived from the existence of a measurable cardinal and in fact derived from the existence of a special type of filters on a cardinal may suggest that by weakening the original properties of a non-principal $\kappa$ &#8211; complete ultrafilter, one can get the &#8220;embeddings&#8221; rather than &#8220;elementary embeddings&#8221; of the universe through the same construction.  </p>
<p>Though, I&#8217;m not sure how to interpret the existence of non-elementary embeddings between each two countable models of ZFC and the difference between the countable and the uncountable cases.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Different models of set theory with the same subset relation by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4476</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4476">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-12T10:58:38Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most permutations of the universe will not be subset-preserving, but if you modify them to act as I do in the first part of the answer, then you get an isomorphic copy of the universe with respect to \in, which has the same induced \subset relation, which is therefore an automorphism with respect to \subset.  The converse is almost true, in the sense that if you have another \in* relation with the same \subset relation, then it is precisely such an isomorphic copy of \in, provided that you can undertake set-theoretic constructions with \in and \in* simultaneously (which is what the class issue is about).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-466</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-466">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-12T09:10:04Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, that&#8217;s what I meant by his autobiographic books. He also has other books in that style. Great books!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Different models of set theory with the same subset relation by David Roberts]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4463</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4463">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-12T01:44:01Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the updated version, Joel, that&#8217;s not unexpected. In a sense the models of set theory are indistinguishable, up to the issue about \in* being a class. What if it has been induced by some class permutation of the usual \in? I don&#8217;t know off the top of my head whether the usual \in is a class or not.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Stefan]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-465</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-465">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-11T21:55:59Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reading &#8220;Surely You&#8217;re Joking, Mr. Feynman!&#8221; is also a very enjoyable way to spend a could and rainy evening. It added Feynman to those handful of people that I miss even though I&#8217;ve never met them in person.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-464</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-464">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-11T16:43:48Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That sounds wonderful. I liked his autobiographic books, full of stories and shenanigans. And a lot of great stories to take with you about scientific integrity.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-463</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-463">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-11T14:32:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoy the Feynman videos.  He was still teaching at Caltech when I was an undergraduate there (mid 1980s), and I took his seminar (Physics X) in the very last semester before his death.  That seminar was totally free-form and open-ended.  Someone would ask a question and then he would riff on it, rather like in this video but in much more detail, and teach us all some subtle but fundamental point in physics or in how we should approach our activity as scientists or how we should think about certain phenomenon.  It was great.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Different models of set theory with the same subset relation by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4444</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4444">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-11T12:36:41Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>David, thanks for this comment, which I find very interesting. You ask what it would look like, and I think it would just be that when you have an isomorphism $\varphi:\langle V,\subseteq\rangle\cong \langle W,\subseteq&#8217;\rangle$, then since we also have $\in$ on $V$, we can impose the induced $\in&#8217;$ on $W$ that corresponds in just that way. That is, we would define $\varphi(x)\in&#8217;\varphi(y)$ just in case $x\in y$. This would make $\varphi$ an isomorphism of $\langle V,\in,\subseteq\rangle$ with $\langle W,\in&#8217;,\subseteq&#8217;\rangle$, and it would mean that $\subseteq&#8217;$ is induced from $\in&#8217;$ in just exactly the isomorphic way that $\subseteq$ is induced from $\in$. In my application (the first part of the post), we have $V=W$ and $\varphi=\tau$, with $\subseteq&#8217;=\subseteq$. So the inclusion relation $\subseteq$ is induced from $\in$ and also from $\in^*$ defined in that way. </p>
<p>Incidentally, I&#8217;ve now added a stronger result to the post, showing that if another class relation $\in^*$ has the same inclusion relation as $\in$, then in fact $\langle V,\in\rangle$ and $\langle V,\in^*\rangle$ are isomorphic. Thus, although the set-membership relation is not definable from inclusion, nevertheless the isomorphism type of it is implicitly definable.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Upward countable closure in the generic multiverse of forcing to add a Cohen real by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/upward-countable-closure-in-the-generic-multiverse-of-forcing-to-add-a-cohen-real/#comment-4417</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/upward-countable-closure-in-the-generic-multiverse-of-forcing-to-add-a-cohen-real/#comment-4417">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T13:59:31Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks very much! I didn&#8217;t know this, but I have now updated with proper credit.  The piece is &#8220;Desire&#8221;, and you can find it on her gallery page at: <a href="http://kingabritschgi.deviantart.com/art/Desire-302267921" rel="nofollow">http://kingabritschgi.deviantart.com/art/Desire-302267921</a>.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Upward countable closure in the generic multiverse of forcing to add a Cohen real by Ali Sadegh Daghighi]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/upward-countable-closure-in-the-generic-multiverse-of-forcing-to-add-a-cohen-real/#comment-4416</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/upward-countable-closure-in-the-generic-multiverse-of-forcing-to-add-a-cohen-real/#comment-4416">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T10:54:51Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think the beautiful picture of this post is a work of the Hungarian artist Kinga Britschgi. </p>
<p>To see more similar works of this artist see the following page:</p>
<p><a href="http://kingabritschgi.deviantart.com/" rel="nofollow">http://kingabritschgi.deviantart.com/</a></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Different models of set theory with the same subset relation by Ali Sadegh Daghighi]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4415</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4415">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T09:20:49Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Domo Arigato for bringing up this subject! <img src="http://jdh.hamkins.org/wp-includes/images/smilies/simple-smile.png" alt=":-)" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> </p>
<p>I still think about the maaning behind your very interesting answer to my MathOverflow question:</p>
<p><a href="http://mathoverflow.net/questions/144231/is-the-inclusion-version-of-kunen-inconsistency-theorem-true" rel="nofollow">http://mathoverflow.net/questions/144231/is-the-inclusion-version-of-kunen-inconsistency-theorem-true</a></p>
<p>In my opinion the corollary stating that one can&#8217;t define $\subseteq$ using $\in$ in a model of set theory has a very deep philosophical content related to the following philosophical questions:</p>
<p>Q1- What is the most &#8220;fundamental&#8221; mathematical object?</p>
<p>Q2- What is the most &#8220;fundamental&#8221; mathematical relation?</p>
<p>Set theorists usually claim that the answer to the questions 1 and 2 are &#8220;set&#8221; and &#8220;membership&#8221; respectively because using these two very simple notions one can build all other mathematical objects and relations. </p>
<p>But this seems an insufficient reasoning for such a big claim. Maybe we can generate all existing mathematical objects and relations (and even more new things) using another &#8220;fundamental&#8221; concepts. </p>
<p>Anyway in order to answer the above questions we first need to clarify what we mean by &#8220;fundamental&#8221;. Maybe the definability provides a nice ground for defining &#8220;fundamentality&#8221; in the sense that if an object or relation is definable from another then it is less fundamental. </p>
<p>Thus the above corollary indicates that &#8220;from ZFC&#8217;s perspective $\in$ is a more fundamental relation than $\subseteq$ because one can define $\subseteq$ from $\in$ but not vice versa&#8221;. </p>
<p>This may look like strange because $\subseteq$ seems a more &#8220;intuitive&#8221; and &#8220;natural&#8221; relation than $\in$ if we notice that in the &#8220;real world&#8221; we can compare &#8220;objects of the same sort&#8221; via $\subseteq$ but this is not the case while talking about $\in$. </p>
<p>For example when we say that the set of students is included in the set of academicians both these &#8220;objects&#8221; are of the same sort namely being the &#8220;set of humans&#8221;. But when we say Ali belongs to the set of academicians, Ali and the set of academicians are of two different sorts namely &#8220;humans&#8221; and &#8220;set of humans&#8221;.</p>
<p>It would be an interesting investigation to characterize all fundamental binary relations of mathematics (and other relations) in an approach similar to above argument via &#8220;definability strength&#8221;, namely determining those relations that could be defined from each other. Specially finding some possible binary relations that are provably different from $\in$ but equi-fundamental with it could be interesting. By equi-fundamental I mean those which can define $\in$. </p>
<p>It is also interesting that investigating such questions can lead one to very deep questions about rigidity of the structure $\langle V, E\rangle$ under different binary relations and in general to the structure of $Aut(\langle V, E\rangle)$ and $Eem(\langle V, E\rangle)$, the classes of automorphisms and self-elementary embeddings of the universe respectively.  </p>
<p>Finally I think this line of thinking may give us a better intuition about the best formulation for &#8220;foundation of mathematics&#8221; and in fact finding an answer to the below question:</p>
<p>Q3- Did we formulate our axioms of mathematics in the best possible way using the most &#8220;fundamental&#8221; objects and relations or there could be some other interesting and more &#8220;intuitive&#8221; concepts and formulations?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Different models of set theory with the same subset relation by David Roberts]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4413</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/different-models-of-set-theory-with-the-same-subset-relation/#comment-4413">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T07:01:13Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your corollary reminds me of the hole paradox (<a href="http://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/hole+argument" rel="nofollow">http://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/hole+argument</a>), which plagued early ideas about representing spacetime by a manifold. In that case, one was trying to think of a point as being ignored by the diffeomorphism of the spacetime manifold and find that lo and behold, the metric at that point is different before and after the diffeomorphism.</p>
<p>If you wrote your construction as a class isomorphism \theta V,\in \to W,\epsilon, and carried across the subset relation you&#8217;d see the analogy with the resolution of the hole paradox. There (i.e. on the nLab page, in the section &#8216;Discussion&#8217;) one uses *two* isomorphisms, where before one had merely the identity map and an automorphism. How would this look for your setup?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Universality and embeddability amongst the models of set theory, CTFM 2015, Tokyo, Japan by Different models of set theory with the same subset relation | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/jdh-hamkins-orguniversality-and-embeddability-ctfm-2015-japan/#comment-4409</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/jdh-hamkins-orguniversality-and-embeddability-ctfm-2015-japan/#comment-4409">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T03:17:40Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] (Rokko-michi-style) okonomiyaki and bi-ru, just like old times, except that we are in Tokyo at the CTFM 2015, and I&#8217;d like to explain the answer, which is yes, this always happens in every model of set [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Comment Board by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/comment-board/#comment-4405</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/comment-board/#comment-4405">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T01:04:17Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My preference in an introductory set theory course is to do some large cardinals before L or forcing. It is relatively easy to develop an analysis of V_kappa and H_kappa for inaccessible cardinals (or the second inaccessible, or Mahlo etc.) and so on, and this introduces the important idea of looking at various models of set theory, and then get to measurable cardinals and ultrapowers.  After this, one can develop L and HOD.  For forcing, I always start first with an extended analysis of MA, to get used to the concepts of density and genericity, but without any need yet for P-names.  After this, one can develop P-names and the forcing extensions a bit more easily.  But I&#8217;ve never been able to do ALL this in one course; it is simply too much.  If they really are seeing ordinals for the first time, then I would be happy if they just get to know some large cardinals and the ultrapower construction, which is something that I think every mathematician should know.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Comment Board by Pedro Sánchez Terraf]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/comment-board/#comment-4404</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/comment-board/#comment-4404">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-10T00:42:22Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Joel,</p>
<p>I need a word of advice (surely won&#8217;t be the last time!). </p>
<p>I&#8217;m preparing a course on Set Theory for next year, and I am expecting a mixed audience;  ranging from graduate students that are starting to study the material (Kunen&#8217;s 1980) as of this writing, to perhaps some undergrads that will have seen basic (though fairly complete) courses on general topology and real variable. Most of them will only have a rudimentary knowledge of logic, and some of them will be seeing the definition of ordinal for the first time.</p>
<p>How much can one afford to compress in a 1-semester course? I&#8217;m just starting to prepare this, but it seems that I could go up to $L$, and perhaps a crash course on the basics of MA (I&#8217;m stealing this idea from some UCLA summer school notes by Justin Palumbo). But perhaps this is just too ambitious&#8230; On the other hand, the people reading Kunen right now are eager to “force”, at least a little bit.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading this, I hope it doesn&#8217;t bother you.</p>
<p>Best wishes,<br />
PST.-</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A question for the mathematics oracle by JN]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/question-for-the-math-oracle/#comment-4396</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/question-for-the-math-oracle/#comment-4396">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-09T13:35:13Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Given the most up to date formal mathematical theory of our physical reality, is it possible to mathematically delineate between the mathematical theories and theorems that express facts found in our real physical reality and those that don&#8217;t ? (excuses if this is silly).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-462</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-462">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-09T07:49:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In all fairness, I think that you&#8217;ve helped me a lot with understanding definitions as well, or at least the gist and outlines of various definitions. I&#8217;d say we&#8217;re more or less even&#8230; :-P</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by David Roberts]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-461</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-461">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-09T07:19:57Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ah, the fun of understanding definitions. You&#8217;ve helped me in that regard in slow and (possibly) painful ways&#8230; I wish I could repay the favour!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The hierarchy of equivalence relations on the natural numbers under computable reducibility by The hierarchy of equivalence relations on the natural numbers under computable reducibility | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/compequiv/#comment-8166</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/compequiv/#comment-8166">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-07T23:24:35Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] See Sam&#8217;s post on this article [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-460</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-460">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-06T05:38:43Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I agree that set theory is generally more abstract than other introductory courses. But I think this phenomenon is all across the board in theoretical mathematics. If you have to apply some creative thinking in verifying the definitions (rather than placing variables into a formula), there will be people not knowing where to begin, and this method will work just fine for them.</p>
<p>This is not about sets as much as it is about doing things non-mechanically.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Mathematical T-Rex by Stefan]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/mathematical-t-rex/#comment-459</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/mathematical-t-rex/#comment-459">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-05T19:37:28Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It wasn&#8217;t the only results in set theory triggering this kind of reaction, but the first that came to mind.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Stefan]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-458</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-458">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-05T19:24:07Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To clarify: By &#8220;your blog&#8221; I mean &#8220;a set theorist&#8217;s blog&#8221;.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on How to solve your problems by Stefan]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-457</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2015/how-to-solve-your-problems/#comment-457">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-05T19:17:23Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not at all surprised to read this sort of post on your blog. Beginning to study set theory, it seemed painfully easy to get things both almost right and utterly wrong. While introductory courses in algebra, analysis and other disciplines often deal with sets in naive and entirely intuitive ways, use and state set theoretical results rather informally and never seem to run into any troubles doing so, the most memorable (and fascinating) aspect of my first course in set theory was realizing how bad things can go wrong!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Asaf Karagila</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Set-theoretic geology by Upward countable closure in the generic multiverse of forcing to add a Cohen real | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/set-theoreticgeology/#comment-4281</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/set-theoreticgeology/#comment-4281">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-04T15:03:51Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] See also my related post, Upward closure in the toy multiverse of all countable models of set theory, which discusses some material appearing in my paper Set-theoretic geology. [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Same Graph, Different Universe by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3797#comment-8017</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3797#comment-8017">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-09-01T20:33:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Submitted to the <em>special issue in memory of Jim Baumgartner</em>, November 2014.<br />
Accepted, September 2015.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',8017)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-8017">1</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Back to the origin… by Even closer to the origin! | François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/984#comment-867</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/984#comment-867">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-08-25T02:44:16Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] three years ago, I wrote &#8220;Back to the origin&#8220;, when I came back to Hanover, New Hampshire. I&#8217;ve now moved to Burlington, Vermont, [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Even closer to the origin!]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1633</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1633">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-08-25T02:44:06Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roughly three years ago, I wrote <q><a href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/984">Back to the origin</a></q>, when I came back to Hanover, New Hampshire. I&#8217;ve now moved to Burlington, Vermont, which is roughly half way between Hanover and Montréal, Québec, which is my true origin. I&#8217;m very happy to start a new position at the <a href="http://uvm.edu">University of Vermont</a>!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Variants of Kelley-Morse set theory by Kelley-Morse set theory implies Con(ZFC) and much more | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/02/24/variants-of-kelley-morse-set-theory/#comment-34028</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/02/24/variants-of-kelley-morse-set-theory/#comment-34028">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-08-08T17:38:18Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] without giving a full formal axiomatization, let us review a little what KM is.  (And please see Victoria Gitman&#8217;s post on variant axiomatizations of KM.)  In contrast to Zermelo-Frankael (ZFC) set theory, which has a purely first-order [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Variants of Kelley-Morse set theory by A natural strengthening of Kelley-Morse set theory, CUNY Logic Workshop, May 2014 | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/02/24/variants-of-kelley-morse-set-theory/#comment-34027</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/02/24/variants-of-kelley-morse-set-theory/#comment-34027">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-08-08T17:38:00Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] theory, including a proof of the folklore fact that KM implies Con(ZFC). This is joint work with Victoria Gitman and Thomas [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on notes by Bonn Mathematical Logic Group, and Common Lisp. | Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/notes/#comment-18</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/notes/#comment-18">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-08-08T17:31:41Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] notes [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A WikiBibtex extension for MediaWiki by Marianne]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33434</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33434">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-07-19T05:16:47Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi Victoria,<br />
I am planning to use WikiBibtex in my own private wiki over the next few years as I am planning to start a PhD. I am currently gathering research tools and trying to decide on a topic to research. It will be in the school of Computer Science, and LaTeX is the go to format. I like using MediaWiki for documentation, so am combining TeX and wiki for my own research purposes.<br />
I will let you know how it goes, and will send suggestions for WikiBibtex.<br />
Thanks for providing a great research tool.<br />
Regards,<br />
Marianne.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A WikiBibtex extension for MediaWiki by Victoria Gitman]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33430</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33430">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-07-18T18:28:50Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi Marianne. Yes, I spotted this typo ages ago, but never got around to fixing it. My apologies! Just change<br />
require_once(\$IP .’/extensions/Biblio/bibtex.php’);<br />
to<br />
require_once(\$IP .’/extensions/WikiBibtex/bibtex.php’);<br />
and everything should work fine (I think you already did this?). I renamed the file &#8216;WikiBibtex&#8217; after I finished the project, but forgot to change the link :). I like my bibtex file better because it gets rid of all the non-essential code in the old bibtex.php (making debugging easier later) and it has some added features for displaying the bib items (which I talked about in the post). If you try both files, let me know which features you liked best where. May I ask what wiki are you planning to use it for?</p>
<p>Honestly, I haven&#8217;t looked at this project since I finished installing it on Peano&#8217;s Parlour ages ago because I have been swamped with research projects :). But your comment is motivating me to go back and work on it some more!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A WikiBibtex extension for MediaWiki by Marianne]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33421</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2014/06/06/a-wikibibtex-extension-for-mediawiki/#comment-33421">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-07-18T04:11:04Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi Victoria,<br />
Nice work with the WikiBibtex extension. I stumbled across it while trying to find any and all MediaWiki extensions for LaTeX. I like the way your extension can put all Bibtex data in the one page.</p>
<p>Installing as directed did not work for me. There is a link in the WikiBibtex.php to;<br />
// Bibtex parser<br />
require_once($IP .&#8217;/extensions/Biblio/bibtex.php&#8217;);</p>
<p>Biblio was not installed, so tried pointing to the bibtex.php you supplied. But I had better results downloading the BibTex extension and pointing to their bibtex.php.<br />
Which bibtex.php I should be using?</p>
<p>I think your extension could be a valuable research tool in MediaWiki. Keep up the good work.<br />
Regards,<br />
Marianne.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Descriptive aspects of torsion-free abelian groups by More students (on whose thesis committees I’ve served) | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/thesis/#comment-7802</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/thesis/#comment-7802">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-07-15T13:51:08Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Abstract.  In recent years, a major theme in descriptive set theory has been the study of the Borel complexity of naturally occurring classification problems. For example, Hjorth and Thomas have shown that the Borel complexity of the isomorphism problem for the torsion-free abelian groups of rank $n$ increases strictly with the rank $n$. In this thesis, we present some new applications of the theory of countable Borel equivalence relations to various classification problems for the $p$-local torsion-free abelian groups of finite rank. Our main result is that when $ngeq 3$, the isomorphism and quasi-isomorphism problems for the $p$-local torsion-free abelian groups of rank $n$ have incomparable Borel complexities. (Here two abelian groups $A$ and $B$ are said to be quasi-isomorphic if $A$ is abstractly commensurable with $B$.) We also introduce a new invariant, the divisible rank, for the class of $p$-local torsion-free abelian groups of finite rank; and we prove that if $ngeq 3$ and $1 leq kleq n − 1$, then the isomorphism problems for the $p$-local torsion-free abelian groups of rank $n$ and divisible rank $k$ have incomparable Borel complexities as $k$ varies. Our proofs rely on the framework developed by Adams and Kechris, whereby cocycle superrigidity results from measurable group theory are applied in the purely Borel setting. In particular, we make use of the recent cocycle superrigidity theorem, due to Ioana, for free ergodic profinite actions of Kazhdan groups.   More [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Stevo’s Forcing Class Fall 2012 – Class 9 by Chris Brown]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2012/10/17/stevos-forcing-class-fall-2012-class-9/#comment-234897</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2012/10/17/stevos-forcing-class-fall-2012-class-9/#comment-234897">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-07-02T23:05:24Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow. I&#8217;ve really enjoyed this series of posts! I gave a presentation on Baumgartner&#8217;s result on ℵ_1-dense sets of reals, but I still haven&#8217;t gotten as deep into forcing as I would like.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The S-space problem, and the cardinal invariant $\mathfrak p$ by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2565#comment-7863</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2565#comment-7863">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-20T20:15:12Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Update: in the <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/malq.201300066" rel="nofollow">following</a> paper, <a href="http://www.ipc.shizuoka.ac.jp/~styorio/" rel="nofollow">T. Yorioka</a> proves an <strong>approximation</strong> of the consistency of PID+$\mathfrak p=\aleph_1$+there are no $S$-spaces.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7863)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7863">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Universal binary sequences by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3346#comment-7847</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3346#comment-7847">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-14T20:34:25Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks, Ashutosh.<br />
The problem is that Meiri and I never decided what to do with the proof. Does the result justify a paper? Does it give generalizations which are not covered by applications of Kronecker’s theorem?<br />
After proving this, we both became busy with other projects and never managed to complete the research around this.</p>
<p>In any case, I can show it to you next Sunday.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7847)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7847">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Universal binary sequences by Ashutosh]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3346#comment-7845</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3346#comment-7845">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-14T20:18:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It would be great if you could post your proof (with Chen Meiri) of the existence of a b-universal sequence of continuum length on your blog when you get a chance.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7845)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7845">1</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on My first Black Board Day by Andrew Tan]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-33045</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-33045">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-14T17:43:42Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow, that&#8217;s awesome! They got the real deal this year.  I&#8217;m a neurobiologist, and gave a short talk about nonstandard models at last year&#8217;s BBD in Austin mainly off your notes which I had found by googling.  All neurobiologists have had to know some logic ever since Goedel, Escher, Bach, but as an amateur (actually, even in stuff in which I&#8217;m supposedly a professional), I never quite know what bit of logic I&#8217;m mangling <img src="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/wp-includes/images/smilies/simple-smile.png" alt=":)" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Indestructibility for Ramsey and Ramsey-like cardinals by Victoria Gitman]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2011/10/21/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals/#comment-32968</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2011/10/21/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals/#comment-32968">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-10T15:31:54Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ah, unfortunately, the status is the same. We just haven&#8217;t had the time to put together the final version :(.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Indestructibility for Ramsey and Ramsey-like cardinals by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2011/10/21/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals/#comment-32964</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2011/10/21/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals/#comment-32964">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-10T13:29:47Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Could you tell me what is the current status of this paper?  I am citing it, and want to use the most current information.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Syndetic colorings with applications to S and L by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3301#comment-7821</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=3301#comment-7821">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-06-06T17:40:44Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Update: a few months ago, Yinhe Peng and Liuzhen Wu answered the above-mentioned question in the affirmative. Their proof will appear in a paper entitled &#8220;A Lindelof topological group with non-Lindelof square&#8221;.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7821)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7821">1</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Contact Me by Stepping up your Math Game – 35 Summer Projects for Post-Secondary Math Students]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/contact-me/#comment-231765</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/contact-me/#comment-231765">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-29T15:47:23Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] a comment on this page, or email me, or PM me on [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Entire functions for which the escaping set is a spider’s web by Entire functions for which the escaping set is a spider’s web | Dave Sixsmith]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/davesixsmith/2015/05/22/some-paper/#comment-11</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/davesixsmith/2015/05/22/some-paper/#comment-11">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-25T09:21:49Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] These slides discuss the results in my paper [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Dave Sixsmith</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A new characterisation of the Eremenko-Lyubich class by A new characterisation of the Eremenko-Lyubich class | Dave Sixsmith]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/davesixsmith/2015/05/23/a-new-characterisation-of-the-eremenko-lyubich-class/#comment-10</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/davesixsmith/2015/05/23/a-new-characterisation-of-the-eremenko-lyubich-class/#comment-10">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-25T08:54:24Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] slides discuss the results in my paper on the Eremenko-Lyubich [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Dave Sixsmith</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on My first Black Board Day by Victoria Gitman]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-32648</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-32648">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-08T00:36:55Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is this a subtle criticism of the blackboard suggestion :)?<br />
But in all earnestness, I think given the length of the seminar, there is absolutely no reason for anyone to want to use slides (unless they are recycling an old talk).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on My first Black Board Day by Miha Habič]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-32643</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/2015/05/07/my-first-black-board-day/#comment-32643">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-07T22:09:54Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before you can declare the seminar as blackboard only, we should probably organize a steady supply of space chalk.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you run for the organizer seat next year, the blackboard chauvinist platform might well work.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Victoria Gitman</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The $\Delta$-system lemma: an elementary proof by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-7751</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-7751">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-05T11:51:16Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The domain of $f$ is the (rather sparse) set $\mathcal A$, so, while you can still think of $f$ as being regressive, the (generalized) Fodor lemma fails in this setup.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7751)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7751">1</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The $\Delta$-system lemma: an elementary proof by Shir Sivroni]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-7750</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-7750">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-05-05T08:01:40Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the second part of the induction step:<br />
 If $|\mathcal A_\tau| &lt; k$ can&#039;t we just define a regressive function $f:\mathcal A \rightarrow k$ where $f(A) = min(A)$?<br />
And then, by fodor&#039;s Lemma and the regularity of $k$, we get to the first part of the induction step?
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7750)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7750">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Infinite chess by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2015/02/25/infinite-chess/#comment-11244</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2015/02/25/infinite-chess/#comment-11244">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-03-02T14:29:07Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I fairly optimistic about it also!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Prikry Forcing by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7598</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7598">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-02-11T19:30:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>that&#8217;s right. thanks for the update!
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7598)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7598">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Prikry Forcing by Mohammad]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7597</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7597">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-02-11T18:46:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I realized that the above argument works when every bounded subset of $\kappa$ is in $V$. </p>
<p>So the above argument does not work for  your case above (Magidor&#8217;s example).
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7597)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7597">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Conjugacy and homogeneous graphs by Conjugacy and homogeneous graphs, II]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/conjugacy-and-homogeneous-graphs/#comment-7580</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/conjugacy-and-homogeneous-graphs/#comment-7580">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-02-04T01:57:41Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] This talk is a continuation of this one. [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Prikry Forcing by Mohammad]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7519</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2156#comment-7519">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-01-19T04:22:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My result is in general; for the Magidor case, take $\kappa^+,$ and note that as he assumes $2^\kappa=\kappa^+,$ so we have $(\kappa^+)^{&lt;\kappa^+}=\kappa^+.$  So if we have a subset of $\kappa^+$ of size $\kappa^+$ in the Prikry extension, then by the above, we have one which has no ground model subset of the same size.
<p class="comment-like"><img class="comment-like-btn" title="Vote" onclick="cl_like_this('http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-admin/admin-ajax.php',7519)" src="http://blog.assafrinot.com/wp-content/plugins/comments-likes/images/like.png" />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span id="comment-like-cnt-7519">0</span> likes</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69528</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69528">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T13:02:31Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks &#8211; I&#8217;ll look up some of those. I hope to go back eventually and expand the note some.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69527</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69527">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T13:00:38Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks. I&#8217;ll need to pull those books by Thomson to see what&#8217;s in there. The surprising thing to me is that this material is apparently not in any introductory logic textbooks.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Peter]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69449</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69449">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T08:13:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not directly related, but Andreas has written lots of stuff on filters and quantifiers, going all the way back to his thesis. His union ultrafilters paper from 1987 has a few comments on quantifiers, his 1993 introductory paper definitely has some treatment (and in my thesis, the definition of idempotent filters comes down to his supervision). </p>
<p>The book by Hindman&amp;Strauss has a section on filters and compactifications in a later chapter &#8212; that might be suitable for 2).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Dave L. Renfro]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-62041</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-62041">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-01T22:09:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What follows mostly repeats a comment I just made on your 1 December 2014 math StackExchange question about this issue. I&#8217;m putting my comment here for anyone who might be interested but doesn&#8217;t visit that site.</p>
<p>Possibly relevant is my October 2004 sci.math post &#8220;Generalized Quantifiers&#8221; (URLs below). FYI, the Math Forum version has a lot of strange formatting errors. See also Brian Thomson&#8217;s 1985 book &#8220;Real Functions&#8221;, and see Thomson&#8217;s earlier 2-part survey Derivation bases on the real line (which contain examples and side-detours not in his book).</p>
<p>google sci.math URL:<br />
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/sci.math/rhZEhXynVLQ/MI0MJ0ZQIvoJ" rel="nofollow">https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/sci.math/rhZEhXynVLQ/MI0MJ0ZQIvoJ</a></p>
<p>Math Forum sci.math URL:<br />
<a href="http://mathforum.org/kb/message.jspa?messageID=3556191" rel="nofollow">http://mathforum.org/kb/message.jspa?messageID=3556191</a></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Some Cardinal Arithmetic by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1593#comment-241</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1593#comment-241">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-11-10T09:54:05Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That&#8217;s very nice. My guess is that each of three addition, multiplication and exponentiation cannot be recovered from the other two. </p>
<p>That been said, assuming the axiom of choice it&#8217;s at least easy to get addition from multiplication and vice versa, for infinite cardinals it&#8217;s easy, for finite cardinals (which can be singled out with either addition or multiplication), addition obviously defines multiplication by induction and multiplication defines the successor ($p+1$ is the unique number such that for all $q$, there is no multiple of $q$ strictly between $qp$ and $q(p+1)$) and by induction we get addition.</p>
<p>Of course the above is much more than an existential formula. And the axiom of choice. My guess, in other words, is that without the axiom of choice, given any formula using just two operations on cardinals, we can find a model of ZF where the formula doesn&#8217;t define the third.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Cardinal Arithmetic]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1593</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1593">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-11-09T20:09:55Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago, Asaf Karagila wrote <a href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2013/provable-equality-of-exponentiation">wonderful post</a> wherein he shows that, even without assuming the axiom of choice one can always find four cardinals <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{p} \lt \mathfrak{q}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{r} \lt \mathfrak{s}\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{p}^{\mathfrak{r}} = \mathfrak{q}^{\mathfrak{s}}.\)</span> In the comments, <a href="http://boolesrings.org/asafk/2013/provable-equality-of-exponentiation/#comment-2024">Harvey Friedman asks</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your theorem is an example of an existential sentence about cardinals in the language with only <span class="math">\(\lt \)</span> and exponentiation. Can you determine which sentences in that language are provable in ZF? More generally, expand the set of sentences about cardinals considered, obviously to include addition and multiplication, and perhaps alternating quantifiers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After <a href="http://boolesrings.org/krautzberger/2014/11/03/tiny-blogging-challenge">Peter Krautzberger&#8217;s tiny blogging challenge</a>, I decided to spend 30 minutes thinking and writing about this&#8230;</p>
<p><span id="more-1593"></span></p>
<p>I will allow myself some liberties in interpreting Friedman&#8217;s open ended question. The celebrated solution of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert%27s_tenth_problem">Hilbert&#8217;s Tenth Problem</a> by Davis, Matiyasevich, Putnam and Robinson shows that the existential theory of the finite cardinal numbers (even without exponentiation) is as complex as it could be: it is <span class="math">\(\Sigma_1\)</span>-complete. I&#8217;ll interpret Friedman&#8217;s question as asking whether the existential theory of all cardinal numbers could be simpler than that of finite cardinals.</p>
<p>My gut instinct is: of course not! But this is not a trivial question. For example asking whether <span class="math">\(p^n + q^n = r^n\)</span> has a solution where <span class="math">\(2 \lt n\)</span> and <span class="math">\(0 \lt p,q,r\)</span> has <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiles%27_proof_of_Fermat%27s_Last_Theorem">proven extremely challenging</a> for finite cardinals but there are plenty of solutions with infinite cardinals!</p>
<p>One plan of attack is to try to define the finite cardinals among all cardinalsusing an existential formula. To get started, I&#8217;ll start with a rich language including constants <span class="math">\(0\)</span>, <span class="math">\(1\)</span>, relations <span class="math">\(=\)</span>, <span class="math">\(\lt \)</span> as well as addition, multiplication and exponentiation. Assuming the Axiom of Choice, finite cardinals are defined by the simple quantifier-free formula <span class="math">\[\mathfrak{p} \lt \mathfrak{p}+1.\]</span> Without assuming choice, this only defines the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dedekind-infinite_set">Dedekind finite sets</a>. Fortunately, if <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{p}\)</span> is infinite then <span class="math">\(2^{2^{\mathfrak{p}}}\)</span> is never Dedekind finite. So the finite sets are always described by the quantifier-free formula <span class="math">\[2^{2^{\mathfrak{p}}} \lt 2^{2^{\mathfrak{p}}} + 1.\]</span> This shows that the existential theory of all cardinals in this rich language is as complex as that of finite cardinals.</p>
<p>Do things change if we restrict the language? Indeed, the first part of Friedman&#8217;s question only mentions exponentiation. For finite cardinals, we can recover addition and multiplication using familiar rules of exponents: <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned}<br />
 a \times b &amp;= c &amp;&amp;\iff&amp; (2^a)^b = 2^c; \\<br />
 a + b &amp;= c &amp;&amp;\iff&amp; (2^{2^a})^{2^b} = 2^{2^c}. \\<br />
\end{aligned}\]</span> We can even eliminate <span class="math">\(0\)</span> and <span class="math">\(1\)</span> since any finite base other than <span class="math">\(0\)</span> and <span class="math">\(1\)</span> will do instead of <span class="math">\(2\)</span>. So, for example, <span class="math">\[a \times b = c \iff \exists x,y,z(x \lt y \land y \lt z \land (z^a)^b = z^c).\]</span> Therefore, the existential theory of finite cardinals with just exponentiation is just as complex as that with addition and multiplication.</p>
<p>Of course, we can&#8217;t use this to recover addition and multiplication of infinite cardinals using the methods we used above, but if we can define the class of finite cardinals then we can use the above to recover addition and multiplication for these cardinals. Can we define finite cardinals using only <span class="math">\(=\)</span>, <span class="math">\(\lt \)</span> and exponentiation? Well, the finite cardinals are the only ones that satisfy the monstrous inequality <span class="math">\[2^{2^{2^{2^{\mathfrak{p}}}}} \lt \left(2^{2^{2^{2^{\mathfrak{p}}}}}\right)^2.\]</span> We can then eliminate <span class="math">\(2\)</span> using the same trick as above to get an existential definition: <span class="math">\[\exists\mathfrak{q},\mathfrak{r},\mathfrak{s}\left(\mathfrak{q} \lt \mathfrak{r} \land \mathfrak{r} \lt \mathfrak{s} \land \mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{p}}}}} \lt \left(\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{s}^{\mathfrak{p}}}}}\right)^{\mathfrak{s}}\right).\]</span> So my gut instinct was right: the existential theory of all cardinals using only <span class="math">\(=\)</span>, <span class="math">\(\lt \)</span> and exponentiation is at least as complex as that of finite cardinals!</p>
<hr />
<p>This took more than 30 minutes but it didn&#8217;t take much more and it was a lot of fun! Hopefully, the time constraint didn&#8217;t impact the content quality too much&#8230;</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on HoTT Math 1: Elementary group theory by On the structure of universes in HoTT | François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1438#comment-206</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1438#comment-206">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-11-08T20:04:07Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] aspects and issues with respect to universes in HoTT. Some of these issues were brought up in a comment discussion with Mike Shulman some time ago and they came up again more recently in a comment discussion with Andrej Bauer and [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Bonn Mathematical Logic Group, and Common Lisp. by Ioanna M. Dimitriou]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/10/29/bonn-mathematical-logic-group-and-common-lisp/#comment-17</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/10/29/bonn-mathematical-logic-group-and-common-lisp/#comment-17">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-10-29T23:00:01Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you, &#8216;saf!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Bonn Mathematical Logic Group, and Common Lisp. by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/10/29/bonn-mathematical-logic-group-and-common-lisp/#comment-16</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/10/29/bonn-mathematical-logic-group-and-common-lisp/#comment-16">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-10-29T20:46:44Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good luck with this project!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Delta-Epsilon Magic by Micheal Pawliuk]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119753</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119753">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-10-09T18:14:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My current (untested, possibly awful) hypothesis is that we should abolish the notion that &#8220;Delta-Epsilon problems have two distinct stages: Rough Work and Proof&#8221; and just stick to the &#8220;proof&#8221; part.</p>
<p>I think this is only really an issue when students have a weak grasp of what constitutes a proof. I&#8217;ve had many students on tests fill a whole back page with work, then on their test page write a very neat and beautiful solution that starts with &#8220;Rough Work: (blah blah blah)&#8221; then &#8220;Proof: (blah blah blah)&#8221;.</p>
<p>Of course, how do you find the delta? Here we start the proof by establishing a relationship between $\vert f(x) &#8211; L \vert$ and $\vert x-a \vert$. In particular, we always want $$\vert f(x) &#8211; L \vert \leq \vert x-a \vert \vert \text{SOMETHING} \vert$$</p>
<p>Then we should be able to &#8220;read off the delta&#8221;. This will work for many examples, although becomes a little trickier with some functions like quadratics.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Delta-Epsilon Magic by Evelyn]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119673</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119673">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-10-09T14:11:27Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s interesting that that was such a powerful experience for you. When I&#8217;m teaching delta-epsilonics in my classes I&#8217;m never sure whether to make a big deal about getting exactly epsilon at the end (and if I do that, should I choose delta right in the beginning or figure it out at the end), or if I should emphasize that any function of epsilon that goes to 0 is good enough, like Asaf says. I kind of alternate between various ways of doing it because I want students to know that if they had to get epsilon at the end they could, but it&#8217;s not nearly as important as whatever they did to bound different parts of the function by something involving epsilon.<br />
Also, I wonder how many students would be inspired by this like you and how many find it intimidating or off-putting. Thanks for sharing and giving me something to think about.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Delta-Epsilon Magic by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119299</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/10/08/delta-epsilon-magic/#comment-119299">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-10-09T00:37:44Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh, I had a teacher like that in my freshman year. He taught me Calculus II. Me and my friends called it &#8220;epsilon magic&#8221; or &#8220;epsilon juggling&#8221;. He would always pick the values to be some strange fractions or other relation functions. And at first it seemed a very peculiar value to choose. But me and my friends (who were pure math undergrads) caught on to this after a couple of times &#8212; you just solve the problem with $\epsilon$, and then you modify the starting value so you&#8217;ll have a nice round result at the end.</p>
<p>I was never a fan of this approach. Not because it obscured something from me, or because it made me feel less capable doing mathematics (calculus had enough effect of that already&#8230; and look at me now, a set theorist!). I do not like this approach because it hinders the mind of the student. Especially at first, the focus goes from &#8220;how to do this&#8221; to &#8220;why <i>this</i> value?&#8221; which is not a good shift of focus, especially at first.</p>
<p>Far better, I think, is to engrave into the student&#8217;s mind that any function of $\epsilon$ which approaches to $0$ would work just fine for these definitions, and after a few times of ending up with a gory result like $2\sqrt{\frac{\epsilon^3}5}$, start using this trick. When the students understand why this magical coefficient was chosen, or whatnot. When the student understands the general reason for choosing these weird values, then it&#8217;s fine to do it.</p>
<p>(My apologies in advance if there are typos, or bad MathJax code. It turned out to be quite a long comment.)</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The conjugacy problem for the automorphism group of the random graph by The conjugacy problem for automorphism groups of countable homogeneous structures]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/summer/#comment-7262</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/summer/#comment-7262">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-09-01T17:19:19Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] This article continues the work of this older one. [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Erdös numbers by Chicago, Baseball and Paul Erdös | Freakonometrics]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2012/05/16/erdos-numbers/#comment-83137</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2012/05/16/erdos-numbers/#comment-83137">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-08-05T21:21:14Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] greatest baseball players of all time&#8221; is supposed to have an Erdös number of 1 (see e.g. <a href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/&#038;#8230" rel="nofollow">http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/&#038;#8230</a>;.). Some pretend that it is only because Hank Aaron has signed the same baseball as Paul Erdös [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Disqus by Szabolcs]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/773#comment-54</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/773#comment-54">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-07-23T20:20:43Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you try to contact Disqus support about this and ask them to implement MathJax support?  If yes, what did they say?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A toolkit for the Dodd-Jensen core model by ioanna]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/06/17/a-toolkit-for-the-dodd-jensen-core-model/#comment-15</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/06/17/a-toolkit-for-the-dodd-jensen-core-model/#comment-15">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-07-03T23:59:24Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m really happy to see that this might be useful to you! Please do send me comments, suggestions, and tell me if something is unclear. And if a measurable cardinal is too weak for your assumptions, I&#8217;m planning of making something similar with the core model for a Woodin cardinal, but I have to finish a proof where I&#8217;m trying this model out first&#8230; (what will be the running example).</p>
<p>I&#8217;m looking forward to meeting you in Munich!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A toolkit for the Dodd-Jensen core model by Victoria Gitman]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/06/17/a-toolkit-for-the-dodd-jensen-core-model/#comment-14</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/06/17/a-toolkit-for-the-dodd-jensen-core-model/#comment-14">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-07-03T17:52:06Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I look forward to reading the note! Since I have given up on making the time to understand all the &#8220;glorious details&#8221; of core models, this might be the perfect introduction :). Great to know that you will be at the Colloquium Logicum! I thought I wouldn&#8217;t know anyone there.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11233</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11233">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-16T17:32:11Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ll be glad to have you back in New York, Norman!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on about by ioanna]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/#comment-13</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/#comment-13">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-16T07:10:13Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you Peter! My first post is almost ready :)</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Norman Lewis Perlmutter]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11232</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11232">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-14T22:42:24Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks, Francois. I think that&#8217;s good advice.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11231</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11231">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-13T23:21:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations Norman!!!</p>
<p>Regarding <q>Moving around every few years for postdocs would be exhausting</q>, I wholeheartedly agree! Every such decision has pros and cons. They are usually not obvious at the outset. Moreover, they change over time. The lesson I learned though my own course is that every decision is right, at least at the time you make it, and there is never any point regretting it later on&#8230; Just keep on doing what you do best all the time!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11230</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-11230">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-13T00:38:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on about by Peter Krautzberger]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/#comment-12</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/#comment-12">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-08T15:46:19Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to BR, Ioanna! Looking forward to reading more!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Senior thesis: Farighon Abdul Rahim by Samuel Coskey]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6630</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6630">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-05-31T19:13:10Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks guys!<br />
We&#8217;ll have to save it for the next project&#8230; <img src="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/wp-includes/images/smilies/simple-smile.png" alt=":)" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Senior thesis: Farighon Abdul Rahim by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6629</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6629">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-05-31T17:05:51Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Assaf, you don&#8217;t need to specify linearity. It follows, just consider $\{a,b\}$, it has a smallest element so $a,b$ are comparable.</p>
<p>I agree about the treatment of Hartogs numbers (and I&#8217;d add their surjective counterparts whom I call Lindenbaum numbers).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Senior thesis: Farighon Abdul Rahim by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6624</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/senior-thesis-farighon-abdul-rahim/#comment-6624">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-05-31T07:07:53Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cheers, Sam!</p>
<p>Two quickies:<br />
a. In Definition 11, needs to be <b>Linearly</b> ordered set.<br />
b. IMHO, any treatment of the axiom of choice would not be complete without mentioning Hartogs&#8217; numbers :).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Absolute Chaos is Impossible! by Blues and Twos]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/01/18/absolute-chaos-is-impossible/#comment-34286</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/01/18/absolute-chaos-is-impossible/#comment-34286">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-04-26T17:09:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello sir,<br />
Thank you for your nice posting.Take four points and put them in a square. By attaching a blue edge or a red edge between each pair of points try to make a configuartion that is “as chaotic as possible”. Whoa! Hold on, I should be careful what I’m saying.<br />
Thanks&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on This was freaky by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/04/01/this-was-freaky/#comment-11168</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/04/01/this-was-freaky/#comment-11168">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-04-02T01:27:23Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I once gave a talk at a gathering of high school students competing in a math olympics contest, and the main thesis I wanted to prove to them was:  It is very likely that rare events occur. We discussed the odds of a particular pattern of outcome when flipping a coin six times.  Any particular pattern, we all agreed, was remote, occurring with probability 1/64.  And then on the stage I actually flipped the coin six times.  But it was manifest that we would get *some* pattern, so I had proved my point, that it was very likely that a rare event occurs. </p>
<p>We went on to look at the paradoxical situations that arise when someone gets a positive test result for a rare disease.  Should they be worried?  If the test is 99% accurate, but the disease occurs in say, 1 in million, then a positive result is not so worrisome: in  million people, there will be about 1 true positive result, and about 10,000 false positives, since 1% of a million is 10,000. So the odds that you&#8217;ve actually got the disease, given that you tested positive, is 1 in 10,000. </p>
<p>But your situation is completely different!  It would be as though we had calculated the odds of getting HHHTTT, and then when I actually flipped the coin on stage, i actually got the same pattern HHHTTT. Totally weird!  And very unlikely.  But you know, if it wasn&#8217;t that, it would have been some other totally unlikely thing, like getting all green lights, or all red lights, or getting the serial number 123456 on your receipt at Starbucks.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by Louis Garde]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-240</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-240">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-28T21:15:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have just discoved your post &#8220;HoTT should eat itself&#8221;. I was thinking at exactly the problem you describe in the post. After reading your article I realize that it is not as easy as I was feeling. And I miss knowledge in model theory to really understand most of the discussion&#8230;</p>
<p>However Following your words: &#8220;That’s just what we need: more people with more different backgrounds and perspectives working on the problem.&#8221;, I will keep going my own way and see if it can lead to anything valuable&#8230; Thanks for your always clear answers.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by Mike Shulman]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-239</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-239">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-27T16:22:34Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t quite understand what you mean, but my best guess is that you&#8217;re suggesting something like Francois says that Andrej suggested: define a universe to be a type of (&#8220;codes for&#8221;) types together with operations exhibiting how all the type-forming operations act on those codes.  The problem with that is, as Francois said and I expanded on above, it won&#8217;t behave judgmentally the way we want universes to behave.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by GARDE]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-238</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-238">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-27T05:59:20Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Mike gave me a pointer to this discussion after a post in HoTT mailing list where I was reporting my frustration with the current definition of Universes in HoTT)</p>
<p>That way looks better to me than the current HoTT&#8217;s  infinite hierarchy of type universes.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m just an amateur with fuzzy type theory knowledge, but it seems to me that an ideal solution would be to be able to define Univeral types in a similar way that we can define Universal Turing machines or Universal diophantine equations.<br />
For this you would need to have fully formalized rules for type construction &#8211; including rules for induction, and higher inductive types (and certainly also a constructive justification for the Univalent axiom).<br />
Any type being able to encode these rules would be a Universal type.</p>
<p>Then it seems to me that no hiearchy of type Universe would be needed any more. The formal rules of type theory would just define what is a (single) universal type. Any other Universal type or hiearchy of Universal types could then be build within the theory.</p>
<p>If this is correct, the problem with Universe is just a side effect of the current lack of complete formalization of type theory.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Hello world! by ioanna]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/03/11/hello-world/#comment-3</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/03/11/hello-world/#comment-3">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-12T12:48:39Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you Joel, I&#8217;m happy to be here! Soon I&#8217;ll make this look like not just a generic (&#8230;) page :)</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Hello world! by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/03/11/hello-world/#comment-2</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/ioanna/2014/03/11/hello-world/#comment-2">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-12T02:37:38Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to Boolesrings, Ioanna!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Ioanna M. Dimitriou Henríquez</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Strange humor by Erin Carmody]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/27/teaching-evaluations/#comment-11163</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/27/teaching-evaluations/#comment-11163">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-01T03:21:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That&#8221;s funny Norm.  I bet the students enjoy your class.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Paper accepted by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/19/300/#comment-11162</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/19/300/#comment-11162">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-02-20T06:35:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations!<br />
You may also be interested in checking out this <a href="http://www.hcm.uni-bonn.de/events/eventpages/2014/infty-final-conference/program/#c5579" rel="nofollow">work</a>.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Give my students homework by Samuel Coskey]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/give-my-students-homework/#comment-6202</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/give-my-students-homework/#comment-6202">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-02-14T23:34:41Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My student noticed that $K$ is not well-founded&#8230; Here is<br />
<a href="http://math.boisestate.edu/m502/hw4/#comment-60" rel="nofollow">his comment on the post</a></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The Day We Fight Back by Samuel Coskey]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/11/283/#comment-11154</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2014/02/11/283/#comment-11154">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-02-12T01:44:59Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Very well said, thank you.</p>
<p>We can start by frowning deeply at the NSA table at the JMM&#8230;</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-237</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-237">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-30T19:20:00Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, this is much closer to what I believe universes in HoTT ought to be. Thanks for the pointer, I will need to look into this&#8230;</p>
<p>It would be great if universe formation could fit into some kind of generalization of higher inductive types. This possibility also puts an interesting spin on the ongoing discussion on the formal rules for higher inductive types in HoTT. Such an approach would also be ontologically much more satisfying than ad hoc approaches such as Super HoTT.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by Mike Shulman]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-236</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-236">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-30T17:48:31Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another possibility to consider is inductive-recursive universes; are you familiar with those?  Inductive-recursive definitions allow you to construct a new &#8220;universe&#8221; inside a given one, containing any specified collection of types and closed under any desired type forming operations, and with judgmental Tarski conversion.  And if you allow a naive sort of &#8220;higher inductive-recursive definition&#8221;, then such a universe can also be univalent (as long as the containing universe is already univalent).</p>
<p>However, we don&#8217;t yet know even whether ordinary inductive-recursive definitions are consistent with the homotopy interpretation, let alone &#8220;higher&#8221; ones.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Super HoTT by François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-235</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543#comment-235">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-30T17:05:32Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Mike, this is very interesting and your comment gave me stuff to think about for a few days&#8230; Yes, it is a desirable feature for Tarski-style coercion to preserve type forming operations judgmentally. Unfortunately, this appears to be somewhat incompatible with the presence of a super universe. I looked for a balance of features here but I couldn&#8217;t reach a definite conclusion.</p>
<p>To recap, for my own benefit and that of others: In the Super HoTT approach there is only one true Tarski-style coercion for the super universe and other universe only have a $\tau:\mathcal{U} \to \mathcal{U}^\ast$ that acts like one but isn&#8217;t one. After composing $\tau$ with the true Tarski-style coercion for the super universe $\mathcal{U}^*$, we can only obtain a weak Tarski-style universe since, for example, there is no obvious way to enforce judgmental equality between $\tau(\pi(A,B))$ and $\prod_{x:\tau(A)} \tau(B(x))$ (as understood by $\mathcal{U}^*$).</p>
<p>This brings up the issue of what judgmental equality is in universes à la Bauer. I haven&#8217;t found a clear choice here. However, whatever it is, it should be required to match between any two <em>cumulative</em> universes (and this should be part of the definition of cumulative in the context of Super HoTT). It&#8217;s not clear whether the super universe should be seen as an accumulation of all smaller universes in Super HoTT (which is basically what requiring $\tau:\mathcal{U}\to\mathcal{U}^*$ to preserve type forming operations judgmentally amounts to).</p>
<p>In my initial conception, this was not the case as I envisioned that different universes might interpret natural numbers and other type differently and sometimes in incompatible ways. That way, for example, classical universes and constructive universes could peacefully inhabit the same super universe. The alternative, to formally see the super universe as an accumulation of all universes, would require some additional machinery such as a formal universe operator, as Palmgren describes. While there are advantages to this, additional heavy machinery would ruin the simplicity of Super HoTT and also reduce (or even eliminate) the need for a super universe.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Give my students homework by François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/give-my-students-homework/#comment-6195</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/scoskey/give-my-students-homework/#comment-6195">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-27T01:11:05Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let me know how it goes for you!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Samuel Coskey</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super HoTT]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1543">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-19T20:31:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a follow-up to my recent post <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1532">on the structure of universes in HoTT</a>. In this post I will outline one of the possible alternative ways of handling universes in HoTT, which I will colorfully call Super HoTT for the time being. This is not an original idea; something like that (not in the context of HoTT) can be found in Erik Palmgren&#8217;s paper <a href="http://www2.math.uu.se/~palmgren/universe.pdf">On Universes in Type Theory</a>.<sup><a href="#notes">1</a></sup> The idea comes from a <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1532#comment-18341">comment by Andrej Bauer</a> where he described a universe as &quot;a structure <span class="math">\((\mathcal{U},\tau,\pi,\sigma,\ldots)\)</span> where <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> is a type, <span class="math">\(\tau\)</span> is a type family indexed by <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U},\)</span> <span class="math">\(\pi\)</span> and <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span> compute codes of dependent products and dependent sums, etc.&quot; This is a perfectly reasonable way of describing universes. By the Foundational Thesis of HoTT, this approach should be formalizable in some flavor of HoTT. This is indeed possible and the flavor (or rather flavor family) Super HoTT is one way to do that.</p>
<p>The issue with Bauer&#8217;s description is the type family <span class="math">\(\tau.\)</span> Formally, a type family indexed by a type <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> is an element <span class="math">\(\tau:\mathcal{U}\to\mathcal{V},\)</span> where <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}\)</span> is some larger universe. This type <span class="math">\(\tau\)</span> becomes a type family only after applying Tarski-style coercion associated to <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}\)</span> that promotes elements of <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}\)</span> to actual types. On the face of it, this is circular: <span class="math">\(\tau\)</span> is the Tarski-style coercion associated to the universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U},\)</span> which is defined in terms of that of <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V},\)</span> which&#8230;</p>
<p>One way to break this circularity is to have a designated <em>super universe</em> <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}^\ast\)</span> — hence the name Super HoTT — whose associated Tarski-style coercion and associated machinery are implemented in the formal system itself. In particular, <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}^\ast\)</span> is associated to a primitive decoding function <span class="math">\(T\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(T(A)\ \mathsf{type}\)</span> for any element <span class="math">\(A:\mathcal{U}^\ast.\)</span> In Super HoTT, this is the only such decoding function. Other universes arise à la Bauer, i.e., as structures <span class="math">\((\mathcal{U},\tau,\pi,\sigma,\ldots)\)</span> where now <span class="math">\(\tau:\mathcal{U}\to\mathcal{U}^\ast\)</span> is a type family that realizes this universe&#8217;s Tarski-style coercion via composition with the super universe&#8217;s decoding function <span class="math">\(T.\)</span> In fact, since there is only one super universe, the Russell-style approach doesn&#8217;t lead to many problems. In other words, there is little harm in suppressing the decoding function <span class="math">\(T\)</span> in favor of a simple Russell-style rule <span class="math">\[\frac{A:\mathcal{U}^\ast}{A\ \mathsf{type}}.\]</span> In fact, the <span class="math">\(\mathsf{type}\)</span> judgment is often informally confounded with an actual universal type <span class="math">\(\mathsf{Type}.\)</span> This type of identification can lead to serious issues such as Girard&#8217;s Paradox; the super universe approach is one of the many safe ways around these problems.</p>
<p>So far, this is pure type theory, we haven&#8217;t said anything HoTT specific. To make this a flavor of HoTT, we postulate that there are enough <em>univalent</em> universes or even lots of them. Universes à la Bauer are mere structures, they can be univalent or not, they can have extra structure or lack some structure. Univalent universes can be identified among these structures so we can formalize a rule saying that any two <span class="math">\(A,B:\mathcal{U}^\ast\)</span> are contained in a univalent universe. One can also formalize rules saying that one can have cumulative univalent universes, cumulative univalent universes with propositional resizing, cumulative classical univalent universes, etc. The possibilities for specialized flavors of Super HoTT are vast and varied!</p>
<p>Note that the super universe doesn&#8217;t have to be univalent. It doesn&#8217;t need to have much fancy structure at all. It&#8217;s not even necessary for <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}^\ast\)</span> to have a natural number type. All of that can happen inside the univalent universes à la Bauer. In fact, a bare-bones super universe is probably more flexible framework than a rich one. Different choices of structure for the super universe and how it interacts with the universes inside it will lead to different flavors of Super HoTT with variable strength. Richer super universe structure allows one to express stronger and stronger properties for the univalent universes it contains.</p>
<p>One advantage of this approach is that universes can arise &quot;on their own&quot; in the sense that any suitable structure <span class="math">\((\mathcal{U},\tau,\pi,\sigma,\ldots)\)</span> is a universe, no matter how it comes about. Though this can be a mixed blessing if one wants more hands-on control over which types are universes. One potential drawback of Super HoTT is that not all types can belong to univalent universes. In particular, the super universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}^\ast,\)</span> cannot belong to any univalent universe inside <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}^\ast.\)</span> In this way, Super HoTT is more like <span class="math">\(\mathsf{NBG}\)</span> or <span class="math">\(\mathsf{MK}\)</span> than <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZF}.\)</span> For ontological reasons, it might be preferable to have a more self-contained system analogously to <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZF}.\)</span> In any case, Super HoTT is one of the more flexible formal ways of handling universes in HoTT and it is a perfectly viable alternative to the formal system presented in the appendix of the <a href="http://homotopytypetheory.org/book/">HoTT book</a>.<sup><a href="#notes">2</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="notes">Notes</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p>E. Palmgren, On universes in type theory. In Twenty-five years of constructive type theory (Venice, 1995), Oxford Logic Guides 36, Oxford University Press, New York, 1998, pages 191–204.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Univalent Foundations Program, Homotopy Type Theory: Univalent Foundations of Mathematics, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, 2013.</p>
</li>
</ol>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Contest Pigeons! by Absolute Chaos is Impossible!]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/01/02/contest-pigeons/#comment-23316</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2014/01/02/contest-pigeons/#comment-23316">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-18T05:01:41Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] &laquo; Contest Pigeons! [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the structure of universes in HoTT]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1532</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1532">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-01-17T03:40:20Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I want to outline some subtle and interesting aspects and issues with respect to universes in HoTT. Some of these issues were brought up in a <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1438">comment discussion with Mike Shulman</a> some time ago and they came up again more recently in a <a href="http://math.andrej.com/2014/01/13/univalent-foundations-subsume-classical-mathematics/">comment discussion with Andrej Bauer and Alexander Kuklev</a>. I will use the <a href="http://homotopytypetheory.org/book/">HoTT book</a> as a reference though this post is not intended as a criticism of the handling of universes in the book. Indeed, to serve its purpose, the book is deliberately vague about the exact handling of universes in HoTT. In fact, this post is a good illustration why this is necessary!</p>
<p>Also note that the issues I bring up are mostly irrelevant to conducting everyday mathematics in HoTT. While this post is largely for people interested in technical aspects of HoTT, I will nevertheless try to keep the the post at a medium level of technicality since these aspects of HoTT do come occasionally up in everyday mathematics.</p>
<p><span id="more-1532"></span></p>
<p>In section 1.3, the HoTT book introduces universes as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[W]e introduce a hierarchy of universes <span class="math">\[\mathcal{U}_0 : \mathcal{U}_1 : \mathcal{U}_2 : \cdots\]</span> where every universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> is an element of the next universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_{i+1}\)</span>. Moreover, we assume that our universes are cumulative, that is that all the elements of the <span class="math">\(i\)</span><sup>th</sup> universe are also elements of the <span class="math">\((i+1)\)</span><sup>st</sup> universe, i.e. if <span class="math">\(A : \mathcal{U}_i\)</span> then also <span class="math">\(A : U_{i+1}.\)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1438">comment discussion</a> mentioned in the preamble, I expressed concerns with the nature of the subscripts in this description. As a result of this discussion, some minor clarification were made to the book. In particular, the following paragraph was added at the end of section 1.3:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As a <em>non</em>-example, in our version of type theory there is no type family &quot;<span class="math">\(\lambda (i:\mathbb{N}).\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span>&quot;. Indeed, there is no universe large enough to be its codomain. Moreover, we do not even identify the indices <span class="math">\(i\)</span> of the universes <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> with the natural numbers <span class="math">\(\mathbb{N}\)</span> of type theory (the latter to be introduced in §1.9).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And further remarks were added in the notes to chapter 1. The purpose of this post is to explain why this matters and also to explain how fiddling with the structure of universes affects HoTT. I will focus on Classical HoTT (HoTT with the Axiom of Choice for sets and hence the Law of Excluded Middle for propositions) though comparable issues arise without these assumptions.</p>
<p>To illustrate the issue, let&#8217;s peek at chapter 10 and in particular at section 10.5, where the book describes the interpretation of the cumulative hierarchy of sets inside HoTT. In any universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> one can find a type <span class="math">\(V_i\)</span> that faithfully interprets the cumulative hierarchy and (since we are working in Classical HoTT) Theorem 10.5.11 shows that <span class="math">\(V_i\)</span> is a model ZFC. In particular, HoTT <em>proves</em> the consistency of ZFC. In fact, HoTT proves the consistency of even stronger theories! With some work, one can show that each <span class="math">\(V_i\)</span> is a level of <span class="math">\(V_{i+1}\)</span> whose ordinal rank <span class="math">\(\kappa_i\)</span> is an inaccessible cardinal in <span class="math">\(V_i.\)</span> Therefore, for each <span class="math">\(i,\)</span> Classical HoTT proves the consistency of <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i,\)</span> where <span class="math">\(\mathsf{IC}_i\)</span> abbreviates the statement &quot;there are at least <span class="math">\(i\)</span> inaccessible cardinals.&quot;</p>
<p>Does this mean that Classical HoTT proves <span class="math">\(\forall i\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span>? No, it doesn&#8217;t. To understand this, remember that <span class="math">\(\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> is a purely arithmetical statement which basically states that there is no proof of <span class="math">\(0 = 1\)</span> from the axioms of <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i.\)</span> Hence <span class="math">\(\forall i\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> is also an arithmetical statement. The only way for HoTT to make sense of this is for <span class="math">\(i\)</span> to range over the type of natural numbers <span class="math">\(\mathbb{N}.\)</span> This is explicitly excluded by the remark quoted above from the end of section 1.3.</p>
<p>The reason for this exclusion becomes more visible if we use an alternative way to handle universes, replacing the hierarchy with a rule which simply says that any two types are contained in a common universe. More precisely (but still suppressing many technical details) given any two types <span class="math">\(A,B\)</span> we can introduce a universe type <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(A, B : \mathcal{U}.\)</span> The above argument showing that Classical HoTT proves the consistency of <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i\)</span> requires <span class="math">\(i\)</span> applications of this rule in order to obtain a sufficiently long chain of universes. Since proofs are finite, a proof can only use the above universe rule finitely often. Therefore, this process does not lead to a proof of <span class="math">\(\forall i:\mathbb{N}\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> in Classical HoTT.</p>
<p>In order to get an actual proof of <span class="math">\(\forall i:\mathbb{N}\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> in we need to have a hierarchy of universes indexed by <span class="math">\(\mathbb{N}.\)</span> More formally, we need a type family <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> which will allow us to use induction on <span class="math">\(\mathbb{N}\)</span> to obtain an actual proof of <span class="math">\(\forall i:\mathbb{N}\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i).\)</span> Doing so, we inadvertently obtain more than we set out. The type family <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> must live in some universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> and the cumulative hierarchy <span class="math">\(V\)</span> associated with this <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> satisfies <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_\omega,\)</span> where <span class="math">\(\mathsf{IC}_\omega\)</span> says that there are infinitely many inaccessible cardinals. Therefore Classical HoTT with the hypothesis of such a family <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> proves <span class="math">\(\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_\omega),\)</span> which is much stronger than what we set out to do.</p>
<p>In fact, Classical HoTT with <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> proves <span class="math">\(\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_{\omega+1}),\)</span> <span class="math">\(\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_{\omega+2}),\)</span> and so on. Why stop there? What if we have a family <span class="math">\(\lambda i:W\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> for every wellordering <span class="math">\(W\)</span>? Can we go beyond? These &quot;large universe hypotheses&quot; are direct analogues of large cardinal hypotheses from set theory. These may seem frivolous at first but such hypotheses <em>necessarily</em> come into play to answer concrete mathematical questions in Classical HoTT such as whether it is possible to extend Lebesgue measure to all subsets of <span class="math">\(\mathbb{R}.\)</span></p>
<p>Let me use this opportunity to point out a feature of the alternative way to handle universes using a rule as outlined above: the rule implies that every type belongs to some universe. The book handles this with this brief remark in section 1.3:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When we say that <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is a type, we mean that it inhabits some universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i.\)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a clever workaround that unfortunately has some side effects. There is no way to formally say &quot;every type belongs to some <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i\)</span>.&quot; The universes <span class="math">\(U_i\)</span> are named constants which means that there is no way to quantify over them. Thus effect of the remark is not to prohibit other types but only to declare anything else to be an &quot;illegetimate&quot; type. The intent is to simplify technical issues but it makes types like <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,U_i\)</span> illegitimate and effectively blocks the possibility of large universe hypotheses as described above.</p>
<p>Mike Shulman suggested a band-aid for this problem in the <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1438">discussion mentioned earlier</a>, pointing out that there could be universes, even legitimate ones, other than the named universes <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i.\)</span> For example, we could introduce an infinite hierarchy of universes in <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_{17}\)</span> if we wanted to. This is true but I do not find this fix fully satisfactory. Universes are very special types that are equipped with a lot of technical machinery to allow elements of universes to become actual types and much more. The book mostly suppresses this machinery, and rightfully so since there are many options which are all very technical and not particularly enlightening. Nevertheless, this machinery is implicitly present and it does not appear on its own. My reading of the syntactic hierarchy used in the book is that this machinery is instantiated for each named universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}_i,\)</span> specifically. To say that there might be other universe suggests that players don&#8217;t have all the rules of the game, which is disconcerting. My alternative proposal with a rule to introduce a universe containing any two types implicitly assumes that there is some form of additional judgment for universes (or similar device) and that this judgment instantiates all the machinery to make a universe. I find this kind of approach more satisfactory since it allows one to add hypotheses such as the existence of <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> without changing the rules of the game.</p>
<p>Let me close by mentioning that there are plenty of alternatives for these issues. For example, it is not necessarily desirable for every type to belong to a universe. While formalizing a proof <span class="math">\(\forall i:\mathbb{N}\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> above, we accidentally proved a lot more because <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> had to live in some universe. If <span class="math">\(\lambda i:\mathbb{N}\,.\,\mathcal{U}_i\)</span> doesn&#8217;t live in a universe, but induction on <span class="math">\(\mathbb{N}\)</span> still works for such types, we can still prove <span class="math">\(\forall i:\mathbb{N}\,\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_i)\)</span> but we can&#8217;t necessarily prove <span class="math">\(\operatorname{Con}(\mathsf{ZFC}+ \mathsf{IC}_\omega)\)</span> as we did above. In fact, there is no need for a single solution: <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ZFC},\)</span> <span class="math">\(\mathsf{NBG},\)</span> <span class="math">\(\mathsf{MK}\)</span> and other set theories have always coexisted pleasantly. However, there is a need to discuss these solutions and to appropriately identify them so that there is no pointless confusion when such aspects of HoTT do matter.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Quiz on public peer review by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13192</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13192">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-11T17:03:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the comment. I do want to point out that I have the copyright to all my papers on the arXiv.  I don&#8217;t know whether any papers there are in the public domain, but the default license grants the arXiv just enough rights to publish the paper, while reserving all other rights for the author. The arXiv, for mathematics, does resolve many issues with peer review, from the delay in dissemination to the cost of paywalls. This, and the practice of speaking about results immediately, long before formal publication, makes the peer review system in mathematics essentially a secondary mechanism for establishing credentials, rather than the primary mechanism for publishing. Unfortunately, there are many scientific disciplines that have nothing analogous to the arXiv, and which do not tend to publicize results before formal publication. The situation in those areas is very different.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Quiz on public peer review by Matthew B]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13184</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13184">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-11T15:02:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think there is no doubt the peer-review process is corrupted: I&#8217;m sure I am not the only one who has seen reviewers with motives/agendas reject work worthy of being published. I&#8217;ve always thought the problem WAS peer-review, so why not just abolish it? Personally, I think ArXiv is the solution to this problem. It is free, there is no copyright, and people can make up their own minds as to whether or not they think it is good.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[HoTT Math 4: Local rings and fields]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1517</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1517">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-10T01:13:28Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a while since the last edition of <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1448">HoTT Math</a>. Fall is always very busy for me and I&#8217;ve been composing this installment one <span class="math">\(\varepsilon\)</span> at a time&#8230; We are finally arriving at our destination: fields!</p>
<p>The main issue with fields is to correctly handle the implicit negation in the term <em>nonzero</em>. Since the natural logic of HoTT is intuitionistic rather than classical, this is much more subtle than one would expect.</p>
<hr />
<p>One issue with the basic commutative ring theory we developed last time is that there is a one-element ring. This is a feature of every equational theory since all identities are satisfied in the trivial algebra with one element. The problem is that equational logic doesn&#8217;t have negation so there is no way to state a nontriviality axiom like <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}\not\approx\mathsf{I}\)</span> in this context. These issues are not new and not special to HoTT but the problem is amplified since logic in HoTT is may have more truth values than just true and false. Consequently, negation in HoTT always needs a little more care.</p>
<p>The usual way to say <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}\not\approx\mathsf{I}\)</span> is the strongest one, namely that <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> is the empty type <span class="math">\(\mathbf{0},\)</span> or: <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$nontrivial$\phantom{q}$}} :\equiv(\mathsf{O}=_R \mathsf{I}) \to \mathbf{0}.\]</span> This is stronger than just saying that <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> isn&#8217;t inhabited and it may exclude more than just the one element ring in the absence of the law of excluded middle [§3.4].</p>
<p>In general, we define inequality by <span class="math">\[(x \neq_R y) :\equiv(x =_R y) \to \mathbf{0}.\]</span> So we can simply write <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}\neq_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> instead of <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$nontrivial$\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span> To see this in action, let&#8217;s look at nonunits. The usual definition gives <span class="math">\[\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x) :\equiv\prod_{y:R} (x \cdot y \neq_R \mathsf{I}).\]</span> The recursion and induction rules for <span class="math">\(\Sigma\)</span>-types [§1.6] show that <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x)\)</span> is equivalent to the negation <span class="math">\(\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) :\equiv\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \to \mathbf{0}.\)</span><sup><a href="#notes">1</a></sup> In classical mathematics, a local ring is one where the nonunits form an ideal, which is then necessarily the unique maximal ideal of the ring. Assuming <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$nontrivial$\phantom{q}$}},\)</span> we see that <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(\mathsf{O})\)</span> is inhabited. It is also easy to see that <span class="math">\[\prod_{x,y:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x)+\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x \cdot y))\]</span> is always inhabited. Thus, all that is missing is the axiom: <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}} :\equiv\prod_{x,y:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x)\times\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x+y)).\]</span> Classically, fields are local rings where the maximal ideal has only one element <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O}.\)</span> So a reasonable axiom for fields is <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}} :\equiv\prod_{x:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x) \to x =_R \mathsf{O}).\]</span> (Note that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> implies <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span>) Classically, these are indeed the fields we know and love but things break down in an intuitionistic setting. If these were fields, then we should be able to conclude that nonzero elements are units. However, from <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> we can only conclude that <span class="math">\(x \neq_R \mathsf{O}\to \lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x)\)</span> and the conclusion there is the double negative <span class="math">\(\lnot\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\)</span> rather than the positive statement <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x).\)</span> The fact is that we cannot conclude that every nonzero element is a unit from this axiom without using the law of excluded middle! A similar issue arises with local rings as defined above: the axiom <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> does not imply the property that if <span class="math">\(x + y\)</span> is a unit then at least one of <span class="math">\(x\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y\)</span> is a unit.</p>
<p>The solution to this isssue is to reverse the relation between equality and inequality. What if instead of inequality being the negation of equality we had that equality was the negation of inequality? This may sound counterintuitive at first but this is often how things work. Consider the case of two computable real numbers <span class="math">\(a\)</span> and <span class="math">\(b,\)</span> that is real numbers for which we have an algorithm which on input <span class="math">\(k\)</span> gives us a rational approximation within <span class="math">\(2^{-k}\)</span> of the real number in question. How do I determine whether <span class="math">\(a\)</span> and <span class="math">\(b\)</span> are equal?</p>
<ul>
<li>To show that they are different, I can use the two algorithms compute sufficiently good rational approximations to <span class="math">\(a\)</span> and <span class="math">\(b\)</span> to tell them apart.</li>
<li>To show that they are equal, I need to argue that they are not different: given any input <span class="math">\(k\)</span> the two algorithms give rational approximations that are within <span class="math">\(2^{1-k}\)</span> of each other.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, for computable real numbers, inequality is more primitive than equality!</p>
<p>This leads us to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apartness_relation">apartness relations</a>: a binary relation <span class="math">\(\mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}\)</span> that satisfies the following two axioms <span class="math">\[\begin{gathered}<br />
\lnot(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}x) \\<br />
x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}y \to x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}z \lor y \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}z<br />
\end{gathered}\]</span> These axioms ensure that the negation of <span class="math">\(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}y\)</span> is an equivalence relation; a tight apartness relation is one where <span class="math">\[\lnot(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}y) \to x = y\]</span> and thus the negation of <span class="math">\(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{}}y\)</span> is equality. In classical logic, every apartness relation is the negation of an equivalence relation but this is not true intuitionistically. In fact, the negation of equality is not necessarily an apartness relation!</p>
<p>Without further ado, let us state exactly how we can define local rings using apartness. For example, a more positive way to define local rings is that <span class="math">\[x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}} y :\equiv\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x &#8211; y)\]</span> is an apartness relation. The first apartness axiom <span class="math">\(\lnot(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}} x)\)</span> actually follows from <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$nontrivial$\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> since <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(\mathsf{O}) \to (\mathsf{O}=_R \mathsf{I}).\)</span> The second apartness axiom boils down to to the fact discussed above that if <span class="math">\(x+y\)</span> is a unit then at least one of <span class="math">\(x\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y\)</span> is a unit. It is tempting to use the type <span class="math">\[\prod_{x:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) + \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y))\]</span> to describe this but this doesn&#8217;t work because of the exclusive nature of sum types. Instead, we must use the propositional truncation <span class="math">\(\Vert\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) + \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)\Vert,\)</span> which is how the logical disjunction <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)\)</span> is defined [§3.7]. Thus a strongly local ring is a a nontrivial ring that satisfies <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} :\equiv\prod_{x,y:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)).\]</span></p>
<p>Before going further with these ideas, let&#8217;s practice some our intuitionistic reasoning by verifying that <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to {\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\]</span> Actually, we won&#8217;t be practicing our intuitionistic reasoning, we&#8217;ll just verify our logic by thinking in terms of functions between types rather than logical implication between propositions. Although an implication is not always equivalent to its contrapositive in intuitionistic logic, we do always have that <span class="math">\[(P \to Q) \to (\lnot Q \to \lnot P).\]</span> In terms of types and functions, this the special case of <span class="math">\[(A \to B) \to ((B \to C) \to (A \to C)),\]</span> where <span class="math">\(A :\equiv{P},\)</span> <span class="math">\(B :\equiv{Q},\)</span> <span class="math">\(C :\equiv\mathbf{0}.\)</span> This looks even more familiar when uncurried: <span class="math">\[(A \to B) \times (B \to C) \to (A \to C).\]</span> Thus, we see that <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to (\lnot(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)) \to \lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y)).\]</span> Now recall that the disjunction <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)\)</span> is defined as the propositional truncation <span class="math">\(\Vert\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) + \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)\Vert\)</span> [§3.7]. This means that <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)\)</span> is a proposition such that <span class="math">\[\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) + \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)) \to P \quad\simeq\quad (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)) \to P\]</span> for any proposition <span class="math">\(P.\)</span><sup><a href="#notes">2</a></sup> Since <span class="math">\(\mathbf{0}\)</span> is a proposition, we see that <span class="math">\[\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \times\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y) \ \simeq\  (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) + \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)) \to \mathbf{0}\ \simeq\  \lnot(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y)),\]</span> where the left equivalence is the special case <span class="math">\(A :\equiv{P},\)</span> <span class="math">\(B :\equiv{Q},\)</span> <span class="math">\(C :\equiv\mathbf{0}\)</span> of <span class="math">\[(A + B) \to C \quad\simeq\quad (A \to C) \times (B \to C).\]</span> Finally, recombining the above, we obtain <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to (\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\times\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y) \to \lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y)),\]</span> which is equivalent to <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to {\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> because <span class="math">\(\lnot\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \leftrightarrow\operatorname{\mathsf{nonunit}}(x).\)</span></p>
<p>Analogously to positive axiom for local rings, the positive axiom for fields is <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} :\equiv\prod_{x:R} (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor x =_R \mathsf{O}),\]</span> which implies both <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> and <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span> To see that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to {\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}},\)</span> we will make use of the distributive law <span class="math">\[(P_1 \lor P_2) \land Q  \quad\leftrightarrow\quad (P_1 \land Q) \lor (P_2 \land Q),\]</span> which follows from the general equivalence <span class="math">\[(A_1 + A_2) \times B \quad\simeq\quad A_1 \times B + A_2 \times B\]</span> by taking propositional truncations. In particular, <span class="math">\[(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor x =_R \mathsf{O}) \times \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \leftrightarrow\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\times\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \lor (x =_R \mathsf{O}) \times \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y).\]</span> Since <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \times \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\)</span> and <span class="math">\((x =_R \mathsf{O}) \times \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \to \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y),\)</span> we see that <span class="math">\[(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor x =_R \mathsf{O}) \times \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x+y) \to (\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) \lor \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(y))\]</span> and it follows that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to {\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span> To see that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}} \to {\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}},\)</span> we will make use of the fact that <span class="math">\[(P \lor Q) \land \lnot Q \to P.\]</span> This also follows from the distributive law above. Indeed, <span class="math">\[(P \lor Q) \land \lnot Q \ \leftrightarrow\  (P \land \lnot Q) \lor (Q \land \lnot Q) \ \leftrightarrow\ P \land \lnot Q\]</span> because <span class="math">\(Q \land \lnot Q\)</span> is <span class="math">\(\mathbf{0}.\)</span> Note that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> is stronger than <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\times{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> since it implies that <span class="math">\[\prod_{x,y:R} (x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}} y \lor x =_R y)\]</span> and thus that <span class="math">\(R\)</span> has decidable equality [§3.4]. In other words, <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> gives the equivalence <span class="math">\[x \neq_R y \leftrightarrow x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}} y,\]</span> which means that <span class="math">\(\neq_R\)</span> is an apartness relation, whereas <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\times{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> only gives that <span class="math">\(\mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}}\)</span> is a tight apartness relation: <span class="math">\[x =_R y \leftrightarrow\lnot(x \mathrel{\rlap{\neq\,}{\,\neq}_{R}} y).\]</span></p>
<p>The analysis above gives <em>three</em> plausible definitions for fields:</p>
<ul>
<li>A <em>residual field</em> is a nontrivial ring that satisfies <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span></li>
<li>A <em>Heyting field</em> is a nontrivial ring that satisfies <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^-\!\!\phantom{q}$}}\)</span> and <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$local${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span></li>
<li>A <em>discrete field</em> is a nontrivial ring that satisfies <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$field${}^+\!\!\phantom{q}$}}.\)</span></li>
</ul>
<p>While each is stronger than the previous, they all have their uses and there is no choice which is always better than the others. Discrete fields behave the same as fields in classical logic since <span class="math">\(R\)</span> has decidable equality. Heyting fields are preferred in constructive circles and most definitions of the field of real numbers yield Heyting fields that are not necessarily discrete [§11.2, §11.3]. While residual fields are harder to work with, they do have their uses since the quotient of a nontrivial ring by a maximal ideal is a residual field which is not necessarily Heyting.</p>
<p>It is common for classical equivalences to break down in intuitionistic logic and therefore many natural concepts that are classically equivalent separate in intuitionistic settings. While this can be an annoyance, it is quite natural in the context of proof-relevant mathematics. Indeed, when we prove that a theorem about fields in a proof-relevant way, we cannot merely argue that every field satisfies the conclusion, we must proceed from known properties of fields and work our way to the desired conclusion. The precise properties used in this process naturally leads to a more refined understanding of the hypotheses of the theorem.</p>
<hr />
<p>Before closing this installment of HoTT Math, let me draw your attention to an important lesson from the above:</p>
<p style="text-align: center"><em>While the logic of HoTT is intuitionistic, knowledge of intuitionistic logic is not necessary to work in HoTT.</em></p>
<p>Thinking in terms of types and functions as we did above works very well. To illustrate once more, consider the following classical equivalences: <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned}<br />
P \to \lnot Q \quad&amp;\leftrightarrow\quad Q \to \lnot P, \\<br />
\lnot P \to Q \quad&amp;\leftrightarrow\quad \lnot Q \to P.<br />
\end{aligned}\]</span> Which are valid in intuitionistic logic? When translated into types and functions, we get that these are the special cases of <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned}<br />
A \to (B \to C) \quad&amp;\simeq\quad B \to (A \to C), \\<br />
(A \to C) \to B \quad&amp;\simeq\quad (B \to C) \to A,<br />
\end{aligned}\]</span> where <span class="math">\(A :\equiv{P},\)</span> <span class="math">\(B :\equiv{Q},\)</span> <span class="math">\(C :\equiv\mathbf{0}.\)</span> The first classical equivalence is intuitionistically valid. After uncurrying both sides of <span class="math">\[A \to (B \to C) \quad\simeq\quad B \to (A \to C),\]</span> we obtain the obvious equivalence <span class="math">\[A \times B \to C \quad\simeq\quad B \times A \to C.\]</span> On the other hand, the general form of the second equivalence makes no sense at all. Taking <span class="math">\(C\)</span> to be just about anything other than <span class="math">\(\mathbf{0}\)</span> leads to obviously false equivalences such as <span class="math">\(\mathbf{1}\to A \simeq\mathbf{1}\to B\)</span> when <span class="math">\(C :\equiv\mathbf{1}.\)</span> Indeed, the second classical equivalence is not intuitionistically valid since taking <span class="math">\(Q :\equiv\lnot P\)</span> leads to <span class="math">\[\lnot P \to \lnot P \quad\leftrightarrow\quad \lnot \lnot P \to P\]</span> and double negation elimination is not intuitionistically valid.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<p>The equivalence of <span class="math">\[\textstyle\prod_{x:A} (B(x) \to C) \quad\simeq\quad \left({\textstyle\sum_{x:A} B(x)}\right)\to C\]</span> is the dependent type analogue of currying/uncurrying. Indeed, if instead of the dependent type <span class="math">\(B:A \to \mathcal{U}\)</span> we have a simple type <span class="math">\(B,\)</span> we obtain the familiar equivalence <span class="math">\[A \to (B \to C) \quad\simeq\quad (A \times B) \to C.\]</span> In full generality, we have the unwieldly equivalence <span class="math">\[\prod_{(a,b):\sum_{x:A} B(x)} C(a,b) \quad\simeq\quad \prod_{a:A} \prod_{b:B(a)} C(a,b),\]</span> where <span class="math">\(B:A \to \mathcal{U}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(C:\sum_{x:A} B(x) \to \mathcal{U}\)</span> [§2.15].</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This is the standard trick to work with propositional truncations: so long as <span class="math">\(P\)</span> is a proposition, <span class="math">\(\Vert A \Vert \to P\)</span> is equivalent to <span class="math">\(A \to P.\)</span> This is very important for handling disjunctions and existential quantifiers. Since <span class="math">\(P \lor Q\)</span> &quot;forgets&quot; which of <span class="math">\(P\)</span> and <span class="math">\(Q\)</span> holds, it is not generally possible to do a case analysis. However, if <span class="math">\(R\)</span> is a proposition then <span class="math">\(P \lor Q \to R\)</span> is equivalent to <span class="math">\(P + Q \to R\)</span> and the coproduct <span class="math">\(P + Q\)</span> does allow for case analysis. This explains why in addition to <span class="math">\[\lnot P \land \lnot Q \quad\leftrightarrow\quad \lnot(P \lor Q),\]</span> the following &quot;halves&quot; of De Morgan&#8217;s laws hold in intuitionistic logic <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned}<br />
P \land Q \quad&amp;\to\quad \lnot(\lnot P \lor \lnot Q), \\<br />
P \lor Q \quad&amp;\to\quad \lnot(\lnot P \land \lnot Q), \\<br />
\lnot P \lor \lnot Q \quad&amp;\to\quad \lnot(P \land Q),<br />
\end{aligned}\]</span> while their converses do not.</p>
</li>
</ol>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Van der Waerden’s Theorem is false for $\omega_1$ by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2013/12/02/van-der-waerdens-theorem-is-false-for-omega_1/#comment-17272</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2013/12/02/van-der-waerdens-theorem-is-false-for-omega_1/#comment-17272">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-03T11:00:49Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You know, if you write the ASCII code backwards in base $p$, where $p$ is a very large prime number, it spells &#8220;I proved the inconsistency of ZFC&#8221;&#8230;</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Van der Waerden’s Theorem is false for $\omega_1$ by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2013/12/02/van-der-waerdens-theorem-is-false-for-omega_1/#comment-17265</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/mpawliuk/2013/12/02/van-der-waerdens-theorem-is-false-for-omega_1/#comment-17265">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-03T08:32:46Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All you need is club<br />
All you need is club<br />
All you need is sparse club<br />
Club is all you need</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Mike Pawliuk</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12641</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12641">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T01:57:04Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw that you&#8217;ll be speaking on this at the JMM (<a href="http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/amsmtgs/2160_abstracts/1096-03-1603.pdf" rel="nofollow">http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/amsmtgs/2160_abstracts/1096-03-1603.pdf</a>), and I shall look forward to it.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12639</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12639">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T00:55:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks, Joel.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12637</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12637">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T00:36:01Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Carl, this is really very nice, and I like it a lot.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on I’ll be at MAMLS October 19-20 by everett]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2013/10/13/ill-be-at-mamls-october-19-20/#comment-8930</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/perlmutter/2013/10/13/ill-be-at-mamls-october-19-20/#comment-8930">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-10-24T03:18:47Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey Norman! </p>
<p>Sorry I missed your call oh-so-many weeks ago. How was the conference?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The logic of Reverse Mathematics by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2011/12/logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-11065</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2011/12/logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-11065">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-09-03T11:41:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks &#8211; I updated the post.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[HoTT Math 3: Unit group of a ring]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1488</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1488">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-07-14T20:30:01Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this installment of <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1448">HoTT Math</a>, we are taking one more step toward elementary field theory by exploring the unit group of a ring.</p>
<hr />
<p>A commutative (unital) ring is a set <span class="math">\(R\)</span> with two constants <span class="math">\(\mathsf{O},\mathsf{I}:1\to R\)</span>, one unary operation <span class="math">\({-\square}:R \to R\)</span>, two binary operations <span class="math">\({\square+\square},{\square\cdot\square}:R \times R \to R\)</span> along with the usual axioms: <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$group$\phantom{q}$}}(\mathsf{O},-\square,\square+\square)\)</span>, <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$monoid$\phantom{q}$}}(\mathsf{I},{\square\cdot\square})\)</span>, <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$distributivity$\phantom{q}$}}({\square+\square},{\square\cdot\square}) : \prod_{x,y,z:R} ((x+y)\cdot z =_R x \cdot z + y \cdot z) \times \prod_{x,y,z:R} (x\cdot(y+z) =_R x \cdot y+x \cdot z),\]</span> and <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$commutativity$\phantom{q}$}}({\square\cdot\square}) : \prod_{x,y:R} (x  \cdot y =_R y \cdot x).\]</span> Commutativity of addition can be derived as usual using the fact that <span class="math">\[x+(x+y)+y =_R (x+y)\cdot(\mathsf{I}+\mathsf{I}) =_R x + (y + x) + y.\]</span> If you want to test your path manipulation skills, you can try to write down the resulting term for <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$commutativity$\phantom{q}$}}({\square+\square}) : \prod_{x,y:R} (x + y =_R y+x).\]</span> However, as we discussed last time, this is not necessary since the proof is ultimately not relevant when the carrier of an algebra is a set.</p>
<p>Reading off the usual definition of unit, we obtain the type <span class="math">\[\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x) :\equiv\sum_{y:R} (x\cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}).\]</span> Elements of type <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\)</span> are pairs <span class="math">\((y,p)\)</span>, where <span class="math">\(y:R\)</span> and <span class="math">\(p: x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>. Because <span class="math">\(R\)</span> is a set and inverses are unique, there is always at most one such <span class="math">\((y,p)\)</span>, which means that <span class="math">\(\operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\)</span> is a proposition. Therefore, we can comprehend the set of units: <span class="math">\[R^\times :\equiv\{x:R \mid \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x)\} :\equiv\sum_{x:R} \operatorname{\mathsf{unit}}(x).\]</span> (Subset comprehension is discussed in §3.5 of the book.) Technically, elements of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> are triples <span class="math">\((x,y,p)\)</span> where <span class="math">\(x,y:R\)</span> and <span class="math">\(p:(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I})\)</span>. Thus <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is not merely a subset of <span class="math">\(R\)</span> but each element of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> comes equipped with a justification for being in <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span>. Since for each <span class="math">\(x:R\)</span> there is at most one <span class="math">\((x,y,p):R^\times\)</span>, we can identify the two without much confusion but the extra coordinates are actually helpful for proving things about <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span>.</p>
<p>To illustrate this, let&#8217;s outline the verification that <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is a group under multiplication. We will view elements of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> as pairs <span class="math">\((x,y)\)</span> but we will forget the path witnessing that <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>. Since we&#8217;re working with sets, we shouldn&#8217;t worry about paths anyway.<sup>1</sup> To begin, we need to isolate the group operations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First, we see that <span class="math">\((\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I}):R^\times\)</span> since we have a path <span class="math">\(\mathsf{I}\cdot\mathsf{I}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> by the identity axiom; this will be our group identity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, we see that if <span class="math">\((x_0,y_0),(x_1,y_1):R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\((x_0 \cdot x_1,y_1 \cdot y_0):R^\times\)</span>. Indeed, if <span class="math">\(x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(x_1 \cdot y_1 =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> then <span class="math">\[x_0 \cdot x_1 \cdot y_1 \cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot \mathsf{I}\cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}.\]</span> From this, we directly extract our group multiplication <span class="math">\(\square\cdot\square:R^\times \times R^\times \to R^\times\)</span>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Finally, we see that if <span class="math">\((x,y):R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\((y,x):R^\times\)</span>. (This is immediate from commutativity but a slightly longer argument shows that this works even without this assumption.) As a result, we get the group inverse <span class="math">\(\square^{-1}:R^\times \to R^\times\)</span>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude the argument, it suffices to verify that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$group$\phantom{q}$}}(R^\times,\square^{-1},\square\cdot\square)\)</span> is inhabited. Associativity and identity are immediate consequences of <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$monoid$\phantom{q}$}}(R,\mathsf{I},\square\cdot\square)\)</span>. The tacit path coordinates are handy for inverses: the path <span class="math">\((x,y)\cdot(y,x) =_{R^\times} (\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I})\)</span> simply consists of the two implied paths <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y \cdot x =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>!</p>
<p>The key difference between this proof and the classical proof that <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is a group is the way we used the definition of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span>. At each step of the classical proof, we need to invoke the definition of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> to get the relevant inverses, do the same computations, and then forget the extra information. In the proof-relevant argument, the subset <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> incorporates its definition and the relevant inverses are already there to be used in computations. To keep the argument from involving too many (ultimately irrelevant) path computations, we still forgot one piece of the definition of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> in the outline above. This kind of selective unraveling can be useful since formal definitions can rapidly become unwieldy. We did end up invoking the path coordinates at the very end to verify the identity axiom. However, we didn&#8217;t really need the paths themselves, we just needed to remember that elements <span class="math">\((x,y)\)</span> aren&#8217;t arbitrary pairs, they are pairs such that <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>. This is what the seemingly irrelevant path coordinate does, the relevant data is not the path itself, it is the type <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> of the path that matters.</p>
<hr />
<p>The lesson is that while proof-relevant mathematics does force you to carry extra baggage, that baggage is actually handy. Moreover, you can always manage the burden by selectively unraveling the contents of the baggage. In fact, you also carry this baggage when doing classical mathematics except that you conceal the baggage in your memory, recalling each item as you need it. The problem with this strategy is that it&#8217;s easy to forget things if you are not careful. Proof-relevant mathematics forces you to keep track of everything!</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="post-scriptum">Post Scriptum</h3>
<p>In the comments, Toby Bartels pointed out that the argument above contains a major type-theoretic <em>faux pas</em>: using type declarations as propositions. The cause of this is the deliberate omission of the path coordinate which leads to phrases like &quot;we see that <span class="math">\((\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I}):R^\times\)</span> since [&#8230;]&quot; and &quot;we see that if <span class="math">\((x,y):R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\((y,x):R^\times\)</span>.&quot; The problem is that type declarations are either correct or not (and this is decidable!) but not true or false. Indeed, true and false are both values that can be used but correct and incorrect are not — there is no value in being incorrect! This may seem like a subtle difference but it is actually a very important one in type theory since there is little other separation of syntax and semantics.</p>
<p>Below, I produced three more variants of the above argument that avoid the trouble with Version 0 above. The first is simply does not omit the path coordinates. The second uses the membership relation <span class="math">\(\in\)</span> where the original used an erroneous type declaration. The third is a direct translation of the classical proof, also using the membership relation. To facilitate comparison, I tried to keep the three versions as close as possible to the original. I am curious to know which of the four versions you prefer, or if you have yet another version that you prefer!</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>Version 1.</strong> Let&#8217;s outline the verification that <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is a group under multiplication. To begin, we need to isolate the group operations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First, <span class="math">\((\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I},i):R^\times\)</span> is our group identity where <span class="math">\(i:\mathsf{I}\cdot\mathsf{I}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> is an instance of the identity axiom.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, the group product is defined by <span class="math">\((x_0,y_0,p_0)\cdot(x_1,y_1,p_1) := (x_0 \cdot x_1,y_1 \cdot y_0,q)\)</span>, where <span class="math">\[q:x_0 \cdot x_1 \cdot y_1 \cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot \mathsf{I}\cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}.\]</span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Finally, group inverses are defined by <span class="math">\((x,y,p)^{-1} := (y,x,q)\)</span>, where <span class="math">\(q:y \cdot x =_R x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}.\)</span> (A slightly longer argument shows that this works even without the commutativity assumption.)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude the argument, it suffices to verify that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$group$\phantom{q}$}}(R^\times,\square^{-1},\square\cdot\square)\)</span> is inhabited. Associativity and identity are immediate consequences of <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$monoid$\phantom{q}$}}(R,\mathsf{I},\square\cdot\square)\)</span>. The path <span class="math">\((x,y,p)\cdot(y,x,q) =_{R^\times} (\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I},i)\)</span> is composed of <span class="math">\(p:x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>, <span class="math">\(q:y \cdot x =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>, and the paths must match since <span class="math">\(R\)</span> is a set.</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>Version 2.</strong> Let&#8217;s outline the verification that <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is a group under multiplication. By virtue of univalence, there are multiple ways to look at <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span>. Instead of viewing it as a subset of <span class="math">\(R\)</span> we can also view it as a subset of <span class="math">\(R \times R\)</span>, namely <span class="math">\[R^\times = \{(x,y):R \times R \mid x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\} = \sum_{x,y:R} (x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}).\]</span> Thus <span class="math">\((x,y) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span> denotes the proposition <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}.\)</span> It turns out that this view of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> will be easier to work with. To begin, we need to isolate the group operations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First, we see that <span class="math">\((\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I}) \in_{R\times R} R^\times\)</span> since we have a path <span class="math">\(\mathsf{I}\cdot\mathsf{I}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> by the identity axiom; this will be our group identity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, we see that if <span class="math">\((x_0,y_0),(x_1,y_1) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\((x_0 \cdot x_1,y_1 \cdot y_0) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span> too. Indeed, if <span class="math">\(x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(x_1 \cdot y_1 =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> then <span class="math">\[x_0 \cdot x_1 \cdot y_1 \cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot \mathsf{I}\cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}.\]</span> From this, we directly extract our group multiplication <span class="math">\(\square\cdot\square:R^\times \times R^\times \to R^\times\)</span>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Finally, we see that if <span class="math">\((x,y) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\((y,x) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span> since <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> implies <span class="math">\(y \cdot x =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> by commutativity. (A slightly longer argument shows that this works even for non-commutative rings.) As a result, we get the group inverse <span class="math">\(\square^{-1}:R^\times \to R^\times\)</span>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude the argument, it suffices to verify that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$group$\phantom{q}$}}(R^\times,\square^{-1},\square\cdot\square)\)</span> is inhabited. Associativity and identity are immediate consequences of <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$monoid$\phantom{q}$}}(R,\mathsf{I},\square\cdot\square)\)</span>. The path <span class="math">\((x,y)\cdot(y,x) =_{R^\times} (\mathsf{I},\mathsf{I})\)</span> is composed of <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y \cdot x =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>, which hold because <span class="math">\((x,y), (y,x) \in_{R \times R} R^\times\)</span>.</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>Version 3.</strong> Let&#8217;s outline the verification that <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span> is a group under multiplication. Per definition of <span class="math">\(R^\times\)</span>, we will write <span class="math">\(x \in_R R^\times\)</span> to mean <span class="math">\(\mathsf{unit}(x)\)</span>. To begin, we need to isolate the group operations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First, we see that <span class="math">\(\mathsf{I}\in_{R} R^\times\)</span> since <span class="math">\(\mathsf{I}\cdot\mathsf{I}=_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> by the identity axiom; this will be our group identity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, we see that if <span class="math">\(x_0,x_1 \in_{R} R^\times\)</span> then <span class="math">\(x_0 \cdot x_1 \in_{R} R^\times\)</span> too. Indeed, since <span class="math">\(\mathsf{unit}(x_0)\)</span> and <span class="math">\(\mathsf{unit}(x_1)\)</span> there are <span class="math">\(y_0,y_1:R\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> and <span class="math">\(x_1 \cdot y_1 =_R \mathsf{I}.\)</span> Then <span class="math">\[x_0 \cdot x_1 \cdot y_1 \cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot \mathsf{I}\cdot y_0 =_R x_0 \cdot y_0 =_R \mathsf{I}\]</span> which shows that <span class="math">\(\mathsf{unit}(x_0 \cdot x_1).\)</span> Thus our group multiplication is (the restriction of) the usual ring multiplication.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Finally, we see that if <span class="math">\(x \in_{R} R^\times\)</span> then, by definition of the proposition <span class="math">\(\mathsf{unit}(u)\)</span>, there is a unique <span class="math">\(y:R\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(x \cdot y =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span>. By commutativity, <span class="math">\(y \cdot x =_R \mathsf{I}\)</span> which means that <span class="math">\(y \in_{R} R^\times\)</span> and this <span class="math">\(y\)</span> is the group inverse of <span class="math">\(x\)</span>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude the argument, it suffices to verify that <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$group$\phantom{q}$}}(R^\times,\square^{-1},\square\cdot\square)\)</span> is inhabited. Associativity and identity are immediate consequences of <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{b}$monoid$\phantom{q}$}}(R,\mathsf{I},\square\cdot\square)\)</span>. The remaining identity <span class="math">\(x \cdot x^{-1} =_{R^\times} \mathsf{I}\)</span> follows immediately from the definition of group inverses.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[HoTT Math 2: More on equational logic]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1476</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1476">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-07-14T16:03:09Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last time, I promised we would look at fields. I have to delay this by one or two installments of HoTT Math since there is so much to say and I am struggling to keep these short. This edition of HoTT Math is a continuation of the first. The main lesson of <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1438">HoTT Math 1</a> was that equational logic still works, provided you&#8217;re careful enough. As I was working through some algebra, I realized that I should have been more precise and nuanced. To make things more precise, I will briefly recall some basic universal algebra and then I will talk a little about Birkhoff&#8217;s soundness and completeness theorem for equational logic.</p>
<hr />
<p>A <em>signature</em> is a sequence <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span> of sets indexed by natural numbers. The elements of the set <span class="math">\(\sigma_n\)</span> are intended to be symbols for <span class="math">\(n\)</span>-ary operations (<span class="math">\(0\)</span>-ary operations are simply constants). For example, the signature for rings can be thought as <span class="math">\[(\{0,1\},\{-\},\{+,\cdot\},\varnothing,\varnothing,\dots).\]</span> It is generally assumed that the sets <span class="math">\(\sigma_n\)</span> are mutually disjoint so that each symbol has a definite arity. In the end, only the cardinality of the sets <span class="math">\(\sigma_n\)</span> matters since the particular symbols used for the operations is mostly a matter of taste.</p>
<p>The logic of universal algebra is equational logic. The symbols from the signature <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span> can be strung together to form terms. In addition to the symbols from <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span>, we need an infinite set <span class="math">\(\{x_0,x_1,x_2,\dots\}\)</span> of variable symbols. Formally, terms are defined inductively using the two rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>Every variable symbol is a term.</li>
<li>If <span class="math">\(t_1,\dots,t_n\)</span> are terms and <span class="math">\(f\)</span> is an element of <span class="math">\(\sigma_n\)</span>, then <span class="math">\(ft_1\dots t_n\)</span> is also a term.</li>
</ul>
<p>Equational logic deals with identities of the form <span class="math">\(t \approx s\)</span> where <span class="math">\(t\)</span> and <span class="math">\(s\)</span> are terms. The rules for equational logic are reflexivity, symmetry, transitivity <span class="math">\[\frac{}{t \approx t}, \quad \frac{t \approx s}{s \approx t}, \quad \frac{t \approx s, s \approx r}{t \approx r}\]</span> together with substitution and replacement <span class="math">\[\frac{t \approx s}{t[x/r] \approx s[x/r]}, \quad \frac{s \approx r}{t[x/r] \approx t[x/s]},\]</span> where <span class="math">\([x/r]\)</span> denotes the act of replacing every occurrence of the variable symbol <span class="math">\(x\)</span> with the term <span class="math">\(r\)</span>. We write <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\)</span> to signify that the identity <span class="math">\(t \approx s\)</span> follows using a combination of these rules from the identities in <span class="math">\(\Gamma\)</span>.</p>
<p>An algebra <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A}\)</span> (with signature <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span>) is a type <span class="math">\(A\)</span> together with an interpretation <span class="math">\[I:\left({\textstyle\sum_{n:\mathbb{N}} \sigma_n \times A^n}\right) \to A.\]</span> If <span class="math">\(f\)</span> is a symbol for an <span class="math">\(n\)</span>-ary operation in <span class="math">\(\sigma_n\)</span>, then the interpretation <span class="math">\(f^{\mathfrak{A}}:A^n \to A\)</span> is <span class="math">\[f^{\mathfrak{A}}(a_1,\dots,a_n) := I(f,a_1,\dots,a_n).\]</span> These interpretations can be used to evaluate any term starting from a variable assignment <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}:\mathbb{N}\to A\)</span> in the usual recursive manner: <span class="math">\[x_i^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} := \mathcal{V}(i), \quad (f t_1 \dots t_k)^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} := f^{\mathfrak{A}}(t_1^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}},\dots,t_k^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}).\]</span> The satisfaction relation for the algebra <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A}\)</span> and the identity <span class="math">\(t \approx s\)</span> is then the type <span class="math">\[(\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s) :\equiv \prod_{\mathcal{V}:\mathbb{N}\to A} (t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} =_A s^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}).\]</span> If the carrier <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is a set then each identity type <span class="math">\(t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} =_A s^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}\)</span> has at most one element and hence <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s\)</span> is a proposition with the usual meaning. In the general case, <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s\)</span> can carry substantial path information.</p>
<p>The fact that equational logic is sound and complete for the semantics is called Birkhoff&#8217;s Theorem: <span class="math">\[\Gamma \vdash t \approx s \quad\text{if and only if}\quad \Gamma \vDash t \approx s.\]</span> Clasically, the right hand side means that every algebra <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A}\)</span> with signature <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span>, <em>whose carrier <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is a set</em>, that satisfies all equations in <span class="math">\(\Gamma\)</span> also satisfies <span class="math">\(t \approx s\)</span>. In HoTT, this translates to the type <span class="math">\[(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s) :\equiv \prod_{\mathfrak{A}/\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} \left(\prod_{u \approx v:\Gamma} (\mathfrak{A} \vDash u \approx v) \to (\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s)\right)\]</span> where the outer product is over all set-based algebras <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A}\)</span> with signature <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span>. An alternate interpretation is <span class="math">\[(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} t \approx s) :\equiv \prod_{\mathfrak{A}/\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} \left(\prod_{u \approx v:\Gamma} (\mathfrak{A} \vDash u \approx v) \to (\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s)\right)\]</span> where the outer product is over algebras with signature <span class="math">\(\sigma\)</span> based on any type. Consequently there are two possible ways to interpret Birkhoff&#8217;s Theorem in HoTT!</p>
<p>The first is closest to the classical version:</p>
<p><strong>Weak Birkhoff Theorem.</strong> <em><span class="math">\(\left\Vert\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\right\Vert\)</span> is equivalent to <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s\)</span>.</em></p>
<p>The vertical lines <span class="math">\(\Vert\square\Vert\)</span> indicate that one should take the propositional truncation of <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\)</span> (§3.7). Indeed, when translated into HoTT, <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\)</span> is the type of all proofs of <span class="math">\(t \approx s\)</span> from <span class="math">\(\Gamma\)</span> in equational logic. The propositional truncation agglomerates all these proofs into one and simply asserts the unqualified existence of such a proof. This is necessary since the right hand side <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s\)</span> is a proposition so the backward implication, without propositional truncation, would amount to a canonical choice of proof with basically no information.</p>
<p>On the other hand, <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vDash_{\text{any}} t \approx s\)</span> is much more expressive because of all the possible identity paths. With all that information on hand, it is not so unlikely that we could reconstruct a proof. This suggests another interpretation of Birkhoff&#8217;s Theorem:</p>
<p><strong>Strong Birkhoff Theorem.</strong> <em><span class="math">\(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\)</span> is equivalent to <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} t \approx s\)</span>.</em></p>
<p>As I stated it just now, this is unlikely to be true. However, I suspect it becomes true with some tweaking of <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\)</span> to only allow proofs that are normalized in some sense or to formally identify proofs that are trivial variations of each other. I haven&#8217;t had much time to think about this so I&#8217;ll leave it as an open conjecture for now and hope that I can come back to it later&#8230;</p>
<p>The soundness part (forward implication) of both forms are true. Last time, I emphasized the usefulness of the weak soundness theorem but I forgot to talk about substitution and replacement! We did talk about how paths could be reversed and composed to get symmetry and transitivity; details are in §2.1 of the book. Since I think it&#8217;s important to know what goes on behind the scenes, let&#8217;s talk about the remaining two rules. Unfortunately, and this explains the earlier omission, neither is particularly pleasant.</p>
<p>Substitution works exactly as you expect. An element <span class="math">\(p:(\mathfrak{A} \vDash t \approx s)\)</span> is a function that maps each variable assignment <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}:\mathbb{N}\to A\)</span> to a path <span class="math">\(p(\mathcal{V}):t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} =_A s^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}\)</span>. Given a term <span class="math">\(r\)</span> and a variable <span class="math">\(x\)</span>, the corresponding element of <span class="math">\((\mathfrak{A} \vDash t[x/r] \approx s[x/r])\)</span> is the composition of <span class="math">\(p\)</span> with the function that sends each variable assignment <span class="math">\(\mathcal{V}:\mathbb{N}\to A\)</span> to the assignment where all values stay the same except that the value of <span class="math">\(x\)</span> is changed to <span class="math">\(r^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}\)</span>. Verifying that the result really is an element of <span class="math">\(\mathfrak{A} \vDash t[x/r] \approx s[x/r]\)</span> is a tedious computation which is best performed under a rug.</p>
<p>The trick behind replacement is revealed in §2.2: <em>functions are functors</em>. The identity types give each type a higher groupoid structure and functions act functorially in the sense that with any <span class="math">\(f:A \to B\)</span> comes with more functions <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ap}_f\)</span> which translate paths <span class="math">\(p:x =_A y\)</span> into paths <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ap}_f(p):f(x) =_B f(y)\)</span>. The details for soundness of the replacement rule are gory but they are essentially the same as in the classical proof. There is some work needed to single out the variable <span class="math">\(x\)</span> and interpret the term <span class="math">\(t\)</span> as a function <span class="math">\(t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}_x:A \to A\)</span> where all other variables are fixed. Then, <span class="math">\(\mathsf{ap}_{t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}_x}\)</span> can be used to transform paths <span class="math">\(s^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}} =_A r^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}\)</span> into paths <span class="math">\(t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}_x(s^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}) =_A t^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}}_x(r^{\mathfrak{A},\mathcal{V}})\)</span>. Thus, we obtain <span class="math">\[(\mathfrak{A} \vDash s \approx r) \to (\mathfrak{A} \vDash t[x/s] \approx t[x/r]).\]</span></p>
<p>Since each rule of equational logic is sound, we therefore have the strong soundness <span class="math">\((\Gamma \vdash t \approx s) \to (\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} t \approx s)\)</span>. To get weak soundness, we compose this with the obvious implication <span class="math">\((\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} t \approx s) \to (\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s)\)</span> and we conclude that <span class="math">\(\left\Vert\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\right\Vert \to (\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s)\)</span> from the fact that <span class="math">\(\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s\)</span> is a proposition. The completenesss part of Birkhoff&#8217;s theorem uses syntactic algebras and HoTT has a really neat way to construct these that we will talk about in a later HoTT Math post.</p>
<hr />
<p>In conclusion, equational logic works just fine in HoTT. In general, because of proof relevance, it is best to keep track of the equational proofs in order to keep track of the identity paths. The strong soundness map <span class="math">\[(\Gamma \vdash t \approx s) \to (\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{any}}} t \approx s)\]</span> guarantees that equational proofs will lead to identities, but different proofs can lead to different identity paths! When the carrier is a set, less care is necessary, the weak soundness map <span class="math">\[\Vert\Gamma \vdash t \approx s\Vert \to (\Gamma \vDash_{\operatorname{\mathsf{set}}} t \approx s)\]</span> shows that the mere existence of an equational proof leads to the desired identities. This is exactly how algebra and equational logic are used classically.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[HoTT Math 1: Elementary group theory]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1438</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1438">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-06-23T18:00:38Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first in a series of posts on doing mathematics in Homotopy Type Theory (HoTT). Various conventions and notations are explained in <a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1448">the preamble</a>; there are no additional prerequisites for this post.</p>
<hr />
<p>A group is a <em>set</em> <span class="math">\(G\)</span> equipped with a constant <span class="math">\(e:1 \to G\)</span>, a unary operation <span class="math">\(\square^{-1}:G \to G\)</span> and a binary operation <span class="math">\({\square\cdot\square}:G \times G \to G\)</span> that satisfy the usual axioms. In HoTT the group axioms must be motivated, so the group <span class="math">\(G\)</span> comes with three more components: <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned}<br />
{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$associativity$\phantom{Q}$}} &amp;: \prod_{x,y,z:G} (x\cdot(y\cdot z) =_G (x\cdot y)\cdot z) \\<br />
{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}} &amp;: \prod_{x:G} (x \cdot e =_G x) \times \prod_{x:G}(e \cdot x = x)\\<br />
{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$inverse$\phantom{Q}$}} &amp;: \prod_{x:G} (e = x^{-1} \cdot x) \times \prod_{x:G} (e =_G x \cdot x^{-1}) \\<br />
\end{aligned}\]</span> The axioms are concrete objects in proof-relevant mathematics! The last two axioms are actually the conjunction of two axioms since conjunction in HoTT correspond to products. It&#8217;s conceptually convenient to package them together and use <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_1\)</span> and <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_2\)</span> for the two conjuncts obtained by applying the projections. In fact, it makes sense to pack all of these into one <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$group$\phantom{Q}$}} :\equiv{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$associativity$\phantom{Q}$}}\times{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}\times{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$inverse$\phantom{Q}$}}\]</span> (but, for the sake of clarity, it is best to refrain from using things like <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$group$\phantom{Q}$}}_1\)</span> for <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$associativity$\phantom{Q}$}}\)</span>).</p>
<p>The axioms types above are parametrized by <span class="math">\(G:\mathsf{Set}\)</span> and the three components <span class="math">\(e\)</span>, <span class="math">\(\square^{-1}\)</span>, <span class="math">\(\square\cdot\square\)</span>, so one can form the type of all groups: <span class="math">\[\mathsf{Grp}:\equiv\sum_{\substack{G:Set\\e:1\to G\\\square^{-1}:G\to G\\\square\cdot\square:G\times G \to G}} {\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$group$\phantom{Q}$}}(G,e,\square^{-1},\square\cdot\square).\]</span> This level of formalism is cumbersome and since it is perfectly clear what the type <span class="math">\(\mathsf{Grp}\)</span> is from the narrative description, it is best to avoid it. The only difference from classical mathematics is that the axioms are given as concrete objects rather than abstract statements.</p>
<p>Familiar identities, for example the fact that <span class="math">\(e\)</span> is its own inverse, can be obtained by combining the group axioms. We have a path <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$inverse$\phantom{Q}$}}_1(e):e =_G e^{-1}\cdot e\)</span> and another path <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_1(e^{-1}):e^{-1}\cdot e =_G e^{-1}\)</span>. Concatenating these two paths yields the desired path <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$inverse$\phantom{Q}$}}_1(e)\cdot{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_1(e^{-1}):e^{-1} =_G e.\]</span><br />
There are other ways to see this, for example, symmetric reasoning yields <span class="math">\[{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$inverse$\phantom{Q}$}}_2(e)\cdot{\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_2(e^{-1}):e^{-1} =_G e.\]</span> In general, these two paths are need not be the same but since <span class="math">\(G\)</span> is a set, i.e., a 0-type, there is at most one path in <span class="math">\(e^{-1} =_G e\)</span> and therefore the two paths above must be the same.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s try something a tad more complicated — <a href="http://mathoverflow.net/questions/5499/which-mathematicians-have-influenced-you-the-most/11379#11379">an old favorite</a> — the uniqueness of identity elements. To say that <span class="math">\(u:G\)</span> is a left identity element means exhibiting an element of the type <span class="math">\[\prod_{x:G} (u \cdot x =_G x);\]</span> so <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_1\)</span> shows that <span class="math">\(e\)</span> is an identity element. Similarly, <span class="math">\({\small\fbox{$\phantom{Q}$identity$\phantom{Q}$}}_2\)</span> shows that <span class="math">\(e\)</span> is a right identity element. Classically, we know that if <span class="math">\(u\)</span> is a left identity and if <span class="math">\(v\)</span> is a right identity then we must have <span class="math">\(u = v\)</span>. In HoTT, this corresponds to exhibiting an element of type <span class="math">\[\mathsf{lrid}:\equiv\prod_{u,v:G} \Big(\prod_{x:G} (u \cdot x =_G x) \times \prod_{y:G} (y \cdot v =_G y) \to (u =_G v)\Big).\]</span></p>
<p>To prove this, let&#8217;s fix <span class="math">\(u,v:G\)</span>. Given <span class="math">\(p:\prod_{x:G} (u \cdot x =_G x)\)</span> and <span class="math">\(q:\prod_{y:G} (y \cdot v =_G y)\)</span> we have paths <span class="math">\[\begin{aligned} p(v) &amp;: u \cdot v =_G v, &amp; q(u)&amp;:u \cdot v =_G u,\end{aligned}\]</span> and therefore a path <span class="math">\[q(u)^{-1} \cdot p(v): u =_G v.\]</span> The classical proof would end here but to get the desired element of <span class="math">\(\mathsf{lrid}\)</span>, we need to wrap things up as follows. Since the final path was obtained uniformly from <span class="math">\(p,q\)</span>, we have an element <span class="math">\[\lambda p,q.q(u)^{-1} \cdot p(v):\prod_{x:G} (u \cdot x =_G x) \times \prod_{y:G} (y \cdot v =_G y) \to (u =_G v)\]</span> and we can then unfix <span class="math">\(u,v:G\)</span> to obtain the desired element <span class="math">\[\lambda u,v.\lambda p,q . q(u)^{-1} \cdot p(v):\mathsf{lrid}.\]</span><br />
I slightly abused <span class="math">\(\lambda\)</span>-notation in the argument above but the idea was only to give a hint how the argument could be formalized. In fact, we did not need to worry about this at all. Since <span class="math">\(G\)</span> is a set, there is at most one path in <span class="math">\(u =_G v\)</span> and thus there is also at most one element in <span class="math">\[\prod_{x:G} (u \cdot x =_G x) \times \prod_{y:G} (y \cdot v =_G y) \to (u =_G v)\]</span> by function extensionality (§4.9). Therefore, the unique choice principle (§3.9) applies to give the desired element of <span class="math">\(\mathsf{lrid}\)</span>. In fact, <span class="math">\(\mathsf{lrid}\)</span> also has exactly one element by function extensionality.</p>
<p>In the end, the classical proof of uniqueness of inverses was sufficient and unambiguous. In fact, the same is true for essentially all similar facts of elementary algebra. This is good for multiple reasons but most importantly this means that doing math in HoTT does not involve getting caught up in elementary stuff like this: you can invoke <span class="math">\(\mathsf{lrid}\)</span> any time without referencing a particular proof since the proof is unique. There is one important caveat:</p>
<p style="text-align: center"><strong>It is very important that the carrier type of a group is a set!</strong></p>
<p>I fell into this trap when I asked <a href="http://mathoverflow.net/questions/134449/equivalent-form-of-the-univalence-axiom">this MathOverflow question</a>. It is very tempting to think that the loop space <span class="math">\(\Omega(A,x) :\equiv(x =_A x)\)</span> is a group for every <span class="math">\(x:A\)</span>. This is only true if <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is a 1-type. Otherwise the carrier of <span class="math">\(\Omega(A,x)\)</span> is not necessarily a 0-type, the uniqueness of paths is lost, <span class="math">\(\mathsf{lrid}\)</span> can have many different proofs, which are all relevant and must not be forgotten!</p>
<hr />
<p>In conclusion, elementary group theory works fine in HoTT. The general feel is a bit different but it&#8217;s more fun than cumbersome to see how the axioms work in relevant mathematics. The same is true for much of elementary algebra and, ultimately, proof relevance is never cumbersome since proofs are almost always unique. It is important to remember that the carrier of an algebraic structure must always be a set for this to work!</p>
<p>In the next installment of HoTT Math, we will continue with elementary field theory which presents an additional difficulty since we must handle the fact that multiplicative inverses do not always exist&#8230;</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[HoTT Math Series]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1448</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1448">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-06-23T18:00:13Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am planning to do a series of posts where I attempt to do math in Homotopy Type Theory (HoTT). The plan is to do some relatively simple proof-relevant mathematics at an informal level. The topics will all be undergraduate level so the mathematics won&#8217;t be hard to follow. I&#8217;m hoping to keep the series brief so each post will only be an appetizer and not a full course dinner. Enjoy!</p>
<p>This preamble will serve to accumulate a table of contents and various conventions and notations that come up along the way. The only prerequisites (or rather corequisites) are the first two chapters of the (free) <a href="http://homotopytypetheory.org/book/">Homotopy Type Theory book</a>. Further prerequisites and reverences to later topics in the book will always be indicated where they occur.</p>
<hr />
<ol>
<li><a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1438">Elementary group theory</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1476">More on equational logic</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1488">Unit group of a ring</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dorais.org/archives/1517">Local rings and fields</a></li>
</ol>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Homotopy Type Theory]]></title>
        <id>http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1425</id>
        <link href="http://logic.dorais.org/archives/1425">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-06-22T16:41:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a productive year at the Institute for Advanced Study, the Univalent Foundations Program has written a book on <a href="http://homotopytypetheory.org/book/">Homotopy Type Theory</a> (HoTT). The foreword gives a succinct description of the purpose of this book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We did not set out to write a book. The present work has its origins in our collective attempts to develop a new style of &quot;informal type theory&quot; that can be read and understood by a human being, as a complement to a formal proof that can be checked by a machine. Univalent foundations is closely tied to the idea of a foundation of mathematics that can be implemented in a computer proof assistant. Although such a formalization is not part of this book, much of the material presented here was actually done first in the fully formalized setting inside a proof assistant, and only later &quot;unformalized&quot; to arrive at the presentation you find before you &mdash; a remarkable inversion of the usual state of affairs in formalized mathematics.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The danger in writing such a book is to fall into the minefields of logic wars. The authors successfully avoided much of these traps, so logicians from other perspectives can read the book without too much cringing. To avoid unnecessary confusion, I recommend mentally substituting most instances of &quot;set theory&quot; by the more apropos &quot;classical mathematics.&quot; Readers from strongly opposing points of view should be prepared for a certain amount of propaganda, which is to be expected in a book written to promote one point of view. Barring these caveats, you will find an enjoyable and well-written book on a very interesting subject. Readers should not be too concerned with the word &quot;homotopy&quot; in the title, homotopy theory is not required background for the book though some basic knowledge of the ideas of topology and homotopy theory helps to understand the motivation behind certain concepts.</p>
<p>Having addressed all the necessary caveats, let&#8217;s talk about why this book is interesting and why you should read it&#8230;</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="what-is-so-hot-about-hott">What is so hot about HoTT?</h3>
<p>The most interesting aspect from my point of view is that HoTT fully supports <em>proof-relevant mathematics</em>, a way of doing mathematics where proofs are real objects that are manipulated on the same level as numbers, sets, functions and all the usual objects of classical mathematics. This is not a brand new idea, logicians have been playing with proofs in this way for a long while, but HoTT brings this idea into the realm of everyday mathematics and that is a major step forward in mathematics.</p>
<p>The key difference with first-order logic is that equality is not primitive. To define a type <span class="math">\(A\)</span> one must also define what equality means for <span class="math">\(A\)</span>. Formally if <span class="math">\(x,y:A\)</span> then <span class="math">\(x =_A y\)</span> (or <span class="math">\(\mathsf{Id}_A(x,y)\)</span>) is another type, an identity type, which can be thought of as made of reasons to identify <span class="math">\(x\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y\)</span>. Elements <span class="math">\(p:x =_A y\)</span> are often called &quot;paths&quot; by analogy with topolgy. Indeed, these paths can be inverted and concatenated to realize symmetry and transitivity of equality, respectively; reflexivity is realized by a path <span class="math">\(\mathsf{refl}_x:x =_A x\)</span>. Thus each type <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is actually a groupoid rather than a plain set. In fact, since each <span class="math">\(x =_A y\)</span> is itself a type with its own identity types and so forth, the type <span class="math">\(A\)</span> is actually a kind of <span class="math">\(\infty\)</span>-groupoid.</p>
<p>It is this rich structure associated with each type is what permits HoTT to support proof relevant mathematics. To get a basic feel of how this works, the statement &quot;<span class="math">\(x =_A y\)</span> and <span class="math">\(y =_A z\)</span>&quot; is interpreted via the product type <span class="math">\((x =_A y)\times(y =_A z)\)</span>, whose elements are pairs of paths that explain why <span class="math">\(x\)</span> is to be identified with <span class="math">\(y\)</span> and why <span class="math">\(y\)</span> is to be identified with <span class="math">\(z\)</span>. Similarly, &quot;<span class="math">\(x =_A y\)</span> or <span class="math">\(y =_A z\)</span>&quot; is interpreted via the coproduct type <span class="math">\((x =_A y) + (y =_A z)\)</span>, whose elements are either paths that explain why <span class="math">\(x\)</span> is to be identified with <span class="math">\(y\)</span> or paths that explain why <span class="math">\(y\)</span> is to be identified with <span class="math">\(z\)</span>. The catch, as you may have guessed from the last example, is that this form of constructive reasoning is intuitionistic and thus not as familiar to mathematicians.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the learning curve for constructive reasoning appears to be much less steep with HoTT than with other constructive frameworks. One of the reasons is that the topological interpretation of the key concepts is very intuitive but more significantly HoTT provides many tools to revert to more familiar territory. The analogue of a plain set in HoTT is a <span class="math">\(0\)</span>-type: a type <span class="math">\(A\)</span> where the identity types <span class="math">\(x =_A y\)</span> always contain at most one path. In other words, these are types where the groupoid structure is trivial and contains no other information than how to handle equality of elements. It is consistent with HoTT that the <span class="math">\(0\)</span>-types form a model of ETCS, a classical theory of sets and functions. Thus, by &quot;truncating&quot; thoughts to <span class="math">\(0\)</span>-types, one can revert to a more familiar classical setting.</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="what-is-the-big-deal-with-univalence">What is the big deal with univalence?</h3>
<p>It is natural to identify things that are not significantly different. For example, the axiom of extensionality in set theory identifies sets that have the same elements since the elements of a set are all that matter in this context. Extensionality for functions identifies functions that agree on all inputs. Univalence is an indiscernibility axiom in the same spirit: it identifies types that are not significantly different.</p>
<p>To make sense of equality for types, we first need to put them in an ambient type, a universe, with its associated identity types. We can&#8217;t have a truly universal type since that directly leads to the usual paradoxes of self-reference. Instead, we have a bunch of universes such that each type belongs to some universe and each universe is closed under the basic type formation rules. Once we have a universe <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> we can talk about equality of types in <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span>, and because <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span> is a type we have a lot of freedom in defining what equality means for types in <span class="math">\(\mathcal{U}\)</span>.</p>
<p>This is exactly what the univalence axiom does. It can be stated elegantly: <span class="math">\[(A \simeq B) \simeq (A =_\mathcal{U} B).\]</span> The equivalence relation <span class="math">\({\simeq}\)</span> is similar to isomorphism but it is slightly more permissive. To say <span class="math">\(A \simeq B\)</span> requires the existence of a function <span class="math">\(f:A \to B\)</span> together with <span class="math">\(\ell,r:B \to A\)</span> such that <span class="math">\(\ell \circ f\)</span> is homotopic to <span class="math">\(\mathsf{id}_A\)</span> and <span class="math">\(f \circ r\)</span> is homotopic to <span class="math">\(\mathsf{id}_B\)</span>. Given two functions <span class="math">\(f\)</span> and <span class="math">\(g\)</span> of the same dependent product type <span class="math">\(\prod_{x:A} B(x)\)</span>, a homotopy from <span class="math">\(f\)</span> to <span class="math">\(g\)</span> is an element of <span class="math">\(\prod_{x:A} (f(x) =_{B(x)} g(x))\)</span>. So <span class="math">\(f\)</span> and <span class="math">\(g\)</span> are homotopic if they agree on all inputs, which does not mean that <span class="math">\(f = g\)</span> in the absence of function extensionality.</p>
<p>In general type theory, <span class="math">\(A \simeq B\)</span> is definitely a good way to say &quot;<span class="math">\(A\)</span> and <span class="math">\(B\)</span> are not siginificantly different&quot; and thus univalence arguably captures the right indiscernibility axiom for type theory. The surprising fact is that such a strong axiom does not appear to collapse more than it should. The benefits of univalence are interesting and need to be explored further.</p>
<hr />
<p>I still need to digest the book so this is probably only the first of many posts on HoTT. The next posts will undoubtedly wander deeper into the technical levels of HoTT. There are a few interesting leads but nothing definite yet.</p>
<p>There is only one thing that bugs me right now, which is the way universes are handled in the book. However, since these assumptions do not appear to be crucial for the development of HoTT and there are plenty of alternatives out there, I&#8217;m not overly concerned about this at the moment.</p>
<p>I will eventually need to talk about higher inductive types. These are really interesting and I&#8217;m happy to see that the book devotes an entire chapter to them. This is a very interesting outgrowth of this project and which deserves study even independently of HoTT.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>François G. Dorais</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Smith Normal Form by MimiTsuruga]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2013/03/22/smith-normal-form-2/#comment-3593</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2013/03/22/smith-normal-form-2/#comment-3593">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-03-28T22:56:57Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oops! Yes, column operations, too. Thanks!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for matsguru</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Smith Normal Form by jesse mckeown]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2013/03/22/smith-normal-form-2/#comment-3590</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2013/03/22/smith-normal-form-2/#comment-3590">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-03-27T01:33:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>just to be annoying&#8230; when you say &#8220;row operations&#8221;, I presume you mean to include column operations as well?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for matsguru</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on KolKom 2012 by Peter Krautzberger]]></title>
        <id>http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2012/11/26/kolkom-2012/#comment-2</id>
        <link href="http://boolesrings.org/matsguru/2012/11/26/kolkom-2012/#comment-2">
        </link>
        <updated>2012-11-26T17:03:35Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome, Mimi!!! So good to have you.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for matsguru</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>