<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Booles&apos; Rings -- Comments</title>
    <link>http://boolesrings.org/</link>
    <updated>2019-01-30T19:45:26Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Booles&apos; Rings</name>
        <email>info@boolesrings.org</email>
        <uri>http://boolesrings.org</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://boolesrings.org/"/>
    <subtitle>Researchers. Connecting.</subtitle>
    <logo>http://boolesrings.org/favicon.gif</logo>
    <rights>No copyright asserted over individual posts; see original posts for copyright and/or licensing.</rights>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Math for nine-year-olds:  fold, punch and cut for symmetry! by 10 fun geometry ideas to share with kids – inspired by a Jordan Ellenberg tweet – Mike's Math Page]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/math-for-nine-year-olds-fold-punch-cut/#comment-9935</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/math-for-nine-year-olds-fold-punch-cut/#comment-9935">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-01-25T15:06:21Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;]  Math for Nine Year Olds -&gt; Joel David Hamkins&#8217;s take on Fold and Punch [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A remark on Schimmerling’s question by Ari Brodsky]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4456#comment-640</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4456#comment-640">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-01-24T00:10:11Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Submitted to Order, November 2017.<br />
Accepted, January 2019.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A question for the mathematics oracle by Vincent R.B. Blazy]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/question-for-the-math-oracle/#comment-9892</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/question-for-the-math-oracle/#comment-9892">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-01-17T12:11:56Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The &#8220;ordinary mathematicians&#8221; aren&#8217;t working in any Model of ZFC, that would exist in some stronger Theory, etc.; they&#8217;re actually working syntactically in ZFC itself! 😊</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The subseries number by The rearrangement and subseries numbers: how much convergence suffices for absolute convergence? Mathematics Colloquium, University of Münster, January 2019 | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-subseries-number/#comment-9848</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-subseries-number/#comment-9848">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-01-10T08:46:45Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] The subseries number. [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Souslin trees at successors of regular cardinals by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4550#comment-635</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4550#comment-635">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-19T06:12:10Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Submitted to Mathematical Logic Quarterly, October 2018.<br />
Accepted, December 2018.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A new proof of the Barwise extension theorem, without infinitary logic, CUNY Logic Workshop, December 2018 by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9567</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9567">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-16T13:12:03Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thinking a bit more about this, it isn&#8217;t clear to me yet how to prove that the types are not principal. I&#8217;ve sent you an email.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A new proof of the Barwise extension theorem, without infinitary logic, CUNY Logic Workshop, December 2018 by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9566</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9566">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-15T12:53:09Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Athar, thanks very much for this. It seems to me that this way of arguing in part amounts to replacing the Keisler-Morley theorem in my argument with the omitting types theorem. That isn&#8217;t too suprising, I suppose, since one can prove the Keisler-Morley theorem by omitting types. But your argument also unifies nicely with the rest of the argument, and so I think it is very nice. I am wondering whether this way of thinking can simply the proof of the universal $\Sigma_1$-definable sequence? The current argument is based on this proof of the Barwise extension theorem, and perhaps we can simplify it via omitting types. I want to think that through. </p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A new proof of the Barwise extension theorem, without infinitary logic, CUNY Logic Workshop, December 2018 by Athar]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9565</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/a-new-proof-of-the-barwise-extension-theorem-cuny-logic-workshop-december-2018/#comment-9565">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-15T01:25:00Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi Joel,</p>
<p>To flesh out my comment from your Q&amp;A session, given a countable M, consider the theory T consisting of the atomic diagram of M, together with ZFC + V = L. You proved that this theory is (finitely) consistent in your &#8220;nonstandard&#8221; case (note that in this proof, we do not need to assume that M is omega nonstandard). So by the omitting types theorem, there is a model N of T such that N is an end extension of M.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The hierarchy of logical expressivity by Stan Letovsky]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-hierarchy-of-logical-expressivity/#comment-9546</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-hierarchy-of-logical-expressivity/#comment-9546">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-09T14:02:20Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Would love to see a lattice of expressivity that includes temporal logics, causal logics, logics of action, higher order, epistemic/doxastic, etc.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The rearrangement number by The rearrangement and subseries numbers: how much convergence suffices for absolute convergence? Mathematics Colloquium, University of Münster, January 2019 | Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-rearrangement-number/#comment-9447</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-rearrangement-number/#comment-9447">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-11-26T14:40:26Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] The rearrangement number. [&#8230;]</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Lectures on the Philosophy of Mathematics, Oxford, Michaelmas 2018 by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics-oxford-michaelmas-2018/#comment-9403</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics-oxford-michaelmas-2018/#comment-9403">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-11-09T18:01:19Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The lectures are in the Oxford Faculty of Philosophy building, the Radcliffe Humanities building, in the Lecture Room on the 2nd floor, Thursdays 12-1.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Lectures on the Philosophy of Mathematics, Oxford, Michaelmas 2018 by Artem Kaznatcheev]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics-oxford-michaelmas-2018/#comment-9401</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics-oxford-michaelmas-2018/#comment-9401">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-11-08T09:27:20Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In which room/time are you giving these lectures? I might want to drop in on the 3 forthcoming ones if there&#8217;s space.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Alan Turing, On computable numbers by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9392</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9392">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-10-13T14:42:48Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, I think we basically agree. I suppose one can say that I have over-stated the case to a certain extent, since it isn&#8217;t actually completely clear from Turing&#8217;s article whether he thought of it just like this. After all, at least on the surface, he does define a computable real number as a kind of real number. But then when one gets into how one might use these, the real number gets replaced by the program. </p>
<p>So in my treatment of this issue in the book I am currently writing on the philosophy of mathematics, I take a somewhat softer tone, while making essentially the same points.</p>
<p>I find these issues quite subtle and interesting, for both mathematical and philosophical reasons.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Alan Turing, On computable numbers by Lorenzo Cocco]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9391</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9391">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-10-13T13:15:11Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think that it is the idea that there are definitions of a term by a different coextensional one that are not *correct* that I was at pains to deny. There are of course interesting questions about how a certain notion and theory are best formalised/analysed when we are not sure at the outset about what sort of entities we want to talk about (reals or programs?). What I got wrong, as Prof. Hamkins pointed out, is that I assumed that the definition had to single out a class of real numbers. But then, on Turing&#8217;s initial definition and on the modern one define, the computable numbers are two different, in fact disjoint classes of programs. They are not coextensional at all. Therefore, again, this does not provide an example of two definitions that are extensionally equivalent but of which one is incorrect.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Alan Turing, On computable numbers by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9390</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9390">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-10-13T12:03:46Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you very much for this knowledgeable and informative comment.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Alan Turing, On computable numbers by Sam Butchart]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9389</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9389">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-10-13T06:58:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for posting this very interesting piece; it is a fascinating topic and your explanation of it was (as usual) very clear and accessible. I think it is a philosophically interesting fact that two definitions can be extensionally equivalent but not equally &#8216;correct&#8217; or &#8216;good&#8217; mathematically speaking. There might be many different kinds of reason why one of a pair of equivalent definitions is preferable to the other. One might be more explanatory, or better support generalisations, or provide a better foundation for a certain kind of theory and so on; it would be interesting to consider further examples and try to classify them.</p>
<p>As a footnote, I think it&#8217;s worth mentioning that Turing himself came to realise that the binary digit representation of real numbers he used in &#8216;On Computable Numbers&#8217; was problematic. He discusses this in &#8216;On Computable Numbers, with an Application to the Entscheidungsproblem. A Correction&#8217; (Proc. London Math. Soc. 43 (1937), 544-6; also reprinted in Jack Copeland (ed) &#8216;The essential Turing&#8217; pp. 94-96).</p>
<p>Turing&#8217;s discussion of the problem (and his solution to it) in this paper is very brief and somewhat cryptic. There is an excellent, detailed discussion of it in Guido Gherardi, &#8216;Alan Turing and the Foundations of Computable Analysis&#8217; , Bulletin of Symbolic Logic 17(3) 2011, 394-430.</p>
<p>In the &#8216;correction&#8217; article, Turing does not discuss the problem you described, that the basic operations on real numbers cannot be represented as computable functions when the binary digit representation is used. Instead he discusses the following problem: although we might have a program P that computes a sequence of rational approximations to a real number <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="&#92;alpha" title="&#92;alpha" class="latex" /> (which we can prove must be computable) there is no program which takes as input programs like P and produces as output a program that enumerates the binary digits of <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="&#92;alpha" title="&#92;alpha" class="latex" />. There must *be* some program that enumerates the digits of <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="&#92;alpha" title="&#92;alpha" class="latex" /> but there&#8217;s no general way of constructing it from a program that computes the sequence of rational approximations. (So the situation seems at least analogous to the problem that there is no program to compute the digits of a + b from programs that enumerate the digits of a and of b).</p>
<p>Turing writes &#8220;This disagreeable situation can be avoided by modifying the manner in which computable numbers are associated with computable sequences, the totality of computable numbers being left unaltered.&#8221; In other words, he offers an alternative definition of &#8216;computable number&#8217; which avoids this problem but which is equivalent to the orginal definition in the sense that a real number is computable in the original sense if and only if it is computable in this new sense &#8211; just as described in your piece. The alternative definition he suggests is not, I believe, the same as any currently standard definition, but is equally workable. He considers sequences of 0s and 1s of the form:</p>
<p><img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="i" title="i" class="latex" /> (0 or 1) followed by 1 repeated <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="n" title="n" class="latex" /> times followed by a 0 followed by a sequence <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c_1&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="c_1" title="c_1" class="latex" /> <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c_2&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="c_2" title="c_2" class="latex" /> <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c_3&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="c_3" title="c_3" class="latex" /> <img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c_4+%5Cldots&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="c_4 &#92;ldots" title="c_4 &#92;ldots" class="latex" /></p>
<p>and associates with each such sequence the real number</p>
<p><img src="//s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%282i+-+1%29n+%2B+%5Csum_%7Br%3D1%7D%5E%7B%5Cinfty%7D%282c_r+-1%29%282%2F3%29%5Er&#038;bg=ffffff&#038;fg=000&#038;s=0" alt="(2i - 1)n + &#92;sum_{r=1}^{&#92;infty}(2c_r -1)(2/3)^r" title="(2i - 1)n + &#92;sum_{r=1}^{&#92;infty}(2c_r -1)(2/3)^r" class="latex" /></p>
<p>So for example the sequence 10 1 corresponds to 2/3, 10 0 corresponds to -2/3, 1110 01 corresponds to 2 + 4/9, 10 11111&#8230; corresponds to 2/3 + 4/9 + 8/27 + &#8230; = 2 and so on.</p>
<p>A Turing machine that prints a sequence of 1s and 0s of this form is then said to compute the corresponding real number; a real number is computable if there is a machine that computes it. Turing cites Brouwer as the source for &#8220;this use of overlapping intervals for the definition of real numbers&#8221;. (See Gherardi section 3.3 for discussion of this).</p>
<p>Turing states (but does not prove) that this new definition solves the problem he discussed. Gherardi proves (section 3.4) that Turing&#8217;s representation is *computably equivalent* to one of the current standard representations (the Cauchy representation) and so it also solves the problem described in your piece &#8211; the standard operations of addition, multiplication and so on are now computable functions.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Alan Turing, On computable numbers by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9388</id>
        <link href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/alan-turing-on-computable-numbers/#comment-9388">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-10-09T09:26:36Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t agree fully with this comment, and I still think it is correct to say that Turing has the wrong definition. </p>
<p>The reason is that we do not ultimately think of a computable real number as a particular kind of real number, and despite his initial definition, neither does Turing. When it comes to defining operations on the computable real numbers, which is what Turing is aiming at, he explicitly abandons the idea that these are defined on the real numbers themselves or some of them. Rather, operations on the computable real numbers are functions defined on the programs that generate such reals. So a computable real number, for Turing as well as for the contemporary theory, is a program for generating a real number.</p>
<p>And if one adopts Turing&#8217;s view that the programs we should be looking at are the programs that generate the successive digits of the real number, then this is precisely where he goes wrong, since in this case, the ordinary operations of addition and multiplication will not be computable, for the reasons I explained in the post. </p>
<p>Turing seems in his article to assume that they would be computable, and much more, since he is using the tangent function and infinite sums and so on. </p>
<p>The philosophical question here as I see it is: what does it mean to have a computable real number? Does it mean to have a particular real number? No, it means to have an algorithm that is capable of describing a real number.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Joel David Hamkins</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Knaster and friends I: Closed colorings and precalibers by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4530#comment-613</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4530#comment-613">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-09-28T23:23:40Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Submitted to Algebra Universalis, June 2018.<br />
Accepted, September 2018.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The $\Delta$-system lemma: an elementary proof by Isaac Gorelic]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-609</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2404#comment-609">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-08-29T05:40:19Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Actually, there is an easier proof (of the Induction step): Either we have a disjoint system of size $\kappa$, or take any maximal disjoint system and some point in its union will belong to  $\kappa$ many (other) members of $\mathcal A$ (that&#8217;s where the regularity of $\kappa$ is needed).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The Engelking-Karlowicz theorem, and a useful corollary by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2054#comment-562</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2054#comment-562">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-05-01T15:23:07Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right. Thank you very much!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The Engelking-Karlowicz theorem, and a useful corollary by DM]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2054#comment-561</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=2054#comment-561">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-05-01T14:01:32Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a typo in the definition of $W$. It should not be $ \mathcal{A} \in [a]^{&lt;\kappa}  $ but $ \mathcal{A} \in [P(a)]^{&lt;\kappa}  $ (where $P(a)$ denotes the power set of $a$).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Distributive Aronszajn trees by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4373#comment-556</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4373#comment-556">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-03-28T20:36:20Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Submitted to Fundamenta Mathematicae, April 2017.<br />
Accepted, March 2018.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Prikry forcing may add a Souslin tree by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4222#comment-422</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4222#comment-422">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-02-14T08:59:16Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It does not, because the proof goes through the proxy principle $P(\lambda^+,\cdots)$ that asserts, among other things, that $\diamondsuit(\lambda^+)$ holds.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Prikry forcing may add a Souslin tree by Mohammad]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4222#comment-421</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4222#comment-421">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-02-14T08:07:21Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Does your result says anything when $2^\lambda &gt; \lambda^+$?</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on A strong form of König’s lemma by saf]]></title>
        <id>http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4433#comment-351</id>
        <link href="http://blog.assafrinot.com/?p=4433#comment-351">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-11-29T06:20:31Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>that&#8217;s right!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Assaf Rinot</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Enjoying new business job by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2016/11/11/enjoying-new-business-job/#comment-43</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2016/11/11/enjoying-new-business-job/#comment-43">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-11-13T15:06:26Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Glad to hear it is working out well, Norman. We miss you in New York &#8212; hope to see you again some time. I think that infinite chess idea may work out!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Resigning from LaGuardia by Ali Sadegh Daghighi]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2016/08/02/resigning-from-laguardia/#comment-42</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2016/08/02/resigning-from-laguardia/#comment-42">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-08-09T18:26:34Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wish you the bests in your life and career, Norman! 🙂</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Resigning from LaGuardia by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2016/08/02/resigning-from-laguardia/#comment-41</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2016/08/02/resigning-from-laguardia/#comment-41">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-08-07T11:41:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ll miss you, Norman! Best of luck for the future.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Infinite chess by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2015/02/25/infinite-chess/#comment-30</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2015/02/25/infinite-chess/#comment-30">
        </link>
        <updated>2015-03-02T14:29:07Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I fairly optimistic about it also!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69528</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69528">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T13:02:31Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks &#8211; I&#8217;ll look up some of those. I hope to go back eventually and expand the note some.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69527</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69527">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T13:00:38Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks. I&#8217;ll need to pull those books by Thomson to see what&#8217;s in there. The surprising thing to me is that this material is apparently not in any introductory logic textbooks.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Peter]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69449</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-69449">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-17T08:13:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not directly related, but Andreas has written lots of stuff on filters and quantifiers, going all the way back to his thesis. His union ultrafilters paper from 1987 has a few comments on quantifiers, his 1993 introductory paper definitely has some treatment (and in my thesis, the definition of idempotent filters comes down to his supervision). </p>
<p>The book by Hindman&amp;Strauss has a section on filters and compactifications in a later chapter &#8212; that might be suitable for 2).</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Filter quantifiers by Dave L. Renfro]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-62041</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2014/11/filter-quantifiers/#comment-62041">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-12-01T22:09:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What follows mostly repeats a comment I just made on your 1 December 2014 math StackExchange question about this issue. I&#8217;m putting my comment here for anyone who might be interested but doesn&#8217;t visit that site.</p>
<p>Possibly relevant is my October 2004 sci.math post &#8220;Generalized Quantifiers&#8221; (URLs below). FYI, the Math Forum version has a lot of strange formatting errors. See also Brian Thomson&#8217;s 1985 book &#8220;Real Functions&#8221;, and see Thomson&#8217;s earlier 2-part survey Derivation bases on the real line (which contain examples and side-detours not in his book).</p>
<p>google sci.math URL:<br />
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/sci.math/rhZEhXynVLQ/MI0MJ0ZQIvoJ" rel="nofollow">https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/sci.math/rhZEhXynVLQ/MI0MJ0ZQIvoJ</a></p>
<p>Math Forum sci.math URL:<br />
<a href="http://mathforum.org/kb/message.jspa?messageID=3556191" rel="nofollow">http://mathforum.org/kb/message.jspa?messageID=3556191</a></p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-29</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-29">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-16T17:32:11Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ll be glad to have you back in New York, Norman!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Norman Lewis Perlmutter]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-28</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-28">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-14T22:42:24Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks, Francois. I think that&#8217;s good advice.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by François G. Dorais]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-27</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-27">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-13T23:21:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations Norman!!!</p>
<p>Regarding <q>Moving around every few years for postdocs would be exhausting</q>, I wholeheartedly agree! Every such decision has pros and cons. They are usually not obvious at the outset. Moreover, they change over time. The lesson I learned though my own course is that every decision is right, at least at the time you make it, and there is never any point regretting it later on&#8230; Just keep on doing what you do best all the time!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Got a tenure-track position at LaGuardia Community College by Asaf Karagila]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-26</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/06/12/got-a-tenure-track-position-at-laguardia-community-college/#comment-26">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-06-13T00:38:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations!</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on This was freaky by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/04/01/this-was-freaky/#comment-25</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/04/01/this-was-freaky/#comment-25">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-04-02T01:27:23Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I once gave a talk at a gathering of high school students competing in a math olympics contest, and the main thesis I wanted to prove to them was:  It is very likely that rare events occur. We discussed the odds of a particular pattern of outcome when flipping a coin six times.  Any particular pattern, we all agreed, was remote, occurring with probability 1/64.  And then on the stage I actually flipped the coin six times.  But it was manifest that we would get *some* pattern, so I had proved my point, that it was very likely that a rare event occurs. </p>
<p>We went on to look at the paradoxical situations that arise when someone gets a positive test result for a rare disease.  Should they be worried?  If the test is 99% accurate, but the disease occurs in say, 1 in million, then a positive result is not so worrisome: in  million people, there will be about 1 true positive result, and about 10,000 false positives, since 1% of a million is 10,000. So the odds that you&#8217;ve actually got the disease, given that you tested positive, is 1 in 10,000. </p>
<p>But your situation is completely different!  It would be as though we had calculated the odds of getting HHHTTT, and then when I actually flipped the coin on stage, i actually got the same pattern HHHTTT. Totally weird!  And very unlikely.  But you know, if it wasn&#8217;t that, it would have been some other totally unlikely thing, like getting all green lights, or all red lights, or getting the serial number 123456 on your receipt at Starbucks.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Strange humor by Erin Carmody]]></title>
        <id>http://normanspace.org/2014/02/27/teaching-evaluations/#comment-24</id>
        <link href="http://normanspace.org/2014/02/27/teaching-evaluations/#comment-24">
        </link>
        <updated>2014-03-01T03:21:37Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That&#8221;s funny Norm.  I bet the students enjoy your class.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Norman Lewis Perlmutter</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Quiz on public peer review by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13192</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13192">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-11T17:03:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the comment. I do want to point out that I have the copyright to all my papers on the arXiv.  I don&#8217;t know whether any papers there are in the public domain, but the default license grants the arXiv just enough rights to publish the paper, while reserving all other rights for the author. The arXiv, for mathematics, does resolve many issues with peer review, from the delay in dissemination to the cost of paywalls. This, and the practice of speaking about results immediately, long before formal publication, makes the peer review system in mathematics essentially a secondary mechanism for establishing credentials, rather than the primary mechanism for publishing. Unfortunately, there are many scientific disciplines that have nothing analogous to the arXiv, and which do not tend to publicize results before formal publication. The situation in those areas is very different.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Quiz on public peer review by Matthew B]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13184</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2012/04/296/#comment-13184">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-12-11T15:02:15Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think there is no doubt the peer-review process is corrupted: I&#8217;m sure I am not the only one who has seen reviewers with motives/agendas reject work worthy of being published. I&#8217;ve always thought the problem WAS peer-review, so why not just abolish it? Personally, I think ArXiv is the solution to this problem. It is free, there is no copyright, and people can make up their own minds as to whether or not they think it is good.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12641</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12641">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T01:57:04Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw that you&#8217;ll be speaking on this at the JMM (<a href="http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/amsmtgs/2160_abstracts/1096-03-1603.pdf" rel="nofollow">http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/amsmtgs/2160_abstracts/1096-03-1603.pdf</a>), and I shall look forward to it.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12639</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12639">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T00:55:52Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks, Joel.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on Talk on Reverse Mathematics and the Modal Logic of Reverse Mathematics by Joel David Hamkins]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12637</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2013/11/talk-on-reverse-mathematics-and-the-modal-logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-12637">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-11-26T00:36:01Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Carl, this is really very nice, and I like it a lot.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment on The logic of Reverse Mathematics by Carl Mummert]]></title>
        <id>http://m6c.org/w/2011/12/logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-11065</id>
        <link href="http://m6c.org/w/2011/12/logic-of-reverse-mathematics/#comment-11065">
        </link>
        <updated>2013-09-03T11:41:29Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks &#8211; I updated the post.</p>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Comments for Carl Mummert</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>